<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The casket of iewels contaynynge a playne description of morall philophie [sic], diligently and after a very easie methode declared by the well learned and famous author Cornelius Valerius: lately turned out of Latin into Englishe, by I.C.</title>
            <author>Valerius, Cornelius, 1512-1578.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1571</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 168 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 95 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14270</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24583</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119018</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854225</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854225</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19634</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14270)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19634)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1042:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The casket of iewels contaynynge a playne description of morall philophie [sic], diligently and after a very easie methode declared by the well learned and famous author Cornelius Valerius: lately turned out of Latin into Englishe, by I.C.</title>
                  <author>Valerius, Cornelius, 1512-1578.</author>
                  <author>Chardon, John, d. 1601.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[164] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By VVilliam Hovv, for Richarde Iohnes,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1571.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>On K8v: This booke translated by Iohn Charlton [i.e. Chardon], late felow of Exetre Colledge, in Oxford, &amp; now schole maister of Wyrksop, in the countie of Nottingham.</note>
                  <note>Latin original not traced.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-K L² .</note>
                  <note>With two final contents leaves.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of a photostat in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery of the original in the British Library.</note>
                  <note>Print covered on D4, H5, and H7 of the photostat; quires D and H from the British Library copy spliced at end.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ethics --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Conduct of life --  Early works to 1900.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19634:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19634:1"/>
            <p>The Caſket of Iewels: Contaynynge a playne deſcription of Morall Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phie, diligently and after a very eaſie Methode declared by the well learned and famous Author Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelius Valerius: Lately turned out of Latin into Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhe, by I. C.</p>
            <q>Inuidia factum premit.</q>
            <p>¶ Imprinted at London, by VVilliam Hovv, for Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charde Johnes. 1571.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:19634:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
                  <head>G C</head>
                  <q>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>RTVS MEA VITA MEA.</q>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:19634:2"/>
            <head>To the Right wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull ſir Ceruis Clyfton Knight, his daily Oratour I. C. vviſſheth longe health with encreaſe of much Worſhip and Vettu.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F we ſhal conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der which thing I do oftentimes with my ſelfe, (right worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Syr) of what dexteritie and ſharpeneſſe of witte, the aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Sages, and pereleſse Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers haue been, with what indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strie and paynefull toyle they haue ſweated in boltynge out the ſecret, and perplexed misteries
<pb facs="tcp:19634:3"/> of Nature, wee haue doubtleſſe an vnſpeakeable occaſion to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce, becauſe through ſuch theyr most excellent workinges we are allured to the knowledge of ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry ſciences: and yet we muſt, or at least we ſhould more bewayle our ſelues, that contemplatynge ſuch worthy documentes and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible principles co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ducing to the manifolde kindes of Godlyneſſe and Vertu, we doo little or no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing prouide for our wealth and commoditie, but rather vnto our greate ſhame and reproche con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe our ſelues wretched bond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, &amp; miſerable captiues to the ſcepter and detestable ſeruitude of Ignorance. For amonge all
<pb facs="tcp:19634:3"/> ſuch benefites which we ſo boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully at their hands haue receiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, no one ſemeth ſo excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, ſo precious, and ſo highli to be prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and yet of vs leſſe folowed and embraced, as is Morall phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy, a matter comprehending the perfect trade how to liue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge men ſoberly and honestly, and ſo directly ſtakinge out the vndeceiueable boundes to the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stell of Vertue, that none can be more apparant only Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stolicall doctrine excepted. Of which when I pondered with my ſelf how greatly the members of the Weale Publike euen at theſe our daies haue neede of, though the cancred infirmitie of a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly
<pb facs="tcp:19634:4"/> minde, had welnie ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsed my conceiued purpoſe, yet aduauncinge against the enſigne of daſtardly courage, &amp; calli<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to my minde the bening cleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy that ſo brightly casteth hir beames from your countenance, and the prone, ready and willyng mynde, zeale and feruent deſier towardes all Godly and vertuous learning, which all men conſider, and I my ſelfe aſſuredly vnderstande, I concluded forthwith to finish this my Translation, that vnder the ſafeward of your Worſhips pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection it may creepe alonge to the behoofe of my Countrey, and the better be fenſed and fortified against the encountring, &amp; wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb facs="tcp:19634:4"/> reprehention of shameleſſe tongues.</p>
            <p>Doubtleſſe (right worshipfull ſir) among ſo many your renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned deedes of Godlyneſſe, this may not be the least, if you shall accept this my industrie and tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell (ſuch as it is) as a token of my hartie goodwill, very deſirous hereby to shew my ſelfe zealous of a friend of ſo worthy a voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And whereas larger mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters cannot be compaſſed, theſe ſimple (ſuch is my confidence) shal not be repelled &amp; reiected: which if I shal perceiue to take a proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous ſucceſſe, henceforth more ſerious indeuour shalbe bestowed to atchiue greater if habilitie,
<pb facs="tcp:19634:5"/> thereunto be correſpondent.</p>
            <p>For I recken all this my labour very feble, and ſclenderly, or no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinge able to preuaile, without your worship were the Fortreſſe hereof, whiche with all my good will and indeuour I dutifully ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibit, not as to learn you any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept in which already you are not exactly ſeene, but by your famous reputation, ſuch is my deſier, to procure it the better credit with others. For when our English youth ſhall contemplate Morall Diſciplyne to be ratified by ſo prudent and graue a Gentelman voyde of all troubleſome moodes of mynde, polished with ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent vnderstandynge, adorned
<pb facs="tcp:19634:5"/> with precious vertues, &amp; practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed profoundly in the experience of politik affaires annexed with Marciall Exploytes, no doubte they and all others will more lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uingly regarde the cauſe, as it is behoueable for them to doo, and more ſpeedely will they ſettle the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues to purſue thoſe fruictfull instructions chiefly to be deſired in a Commonwealth orderly, &amp; diſcretly to be stablished. For herein is compriſed a meane to procure rest and peaſibleneſſe in priuate life, to purchaſe estima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion and dignitie in bearynge of office, in euery degree to diſmou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vnrulineſſe, &amp; conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cious ſturres to ſurpriſe al moodineſse of mind
<pb facs="tcp:19634:6"/> to extirpat incestuous concupiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, and finally to reenforce, ſtrengthen &amp; ſupport an impreg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable rule of vſage, and laudable behauiour. This boke is euidently <hi>the Glaſſe of intelligence: the Theatre of comely conuerſacion: The Stage of honeſt demenour: the Treaſure houſe of Ciuilitie: the Conduite to true Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and eternall Felicitie. It is the Caſket of Ievvels: the Mayſtreſſe of Prudence: the Bulvvarke of equitie: the Palace of Fortitude: the Nurſe of Sober<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: the Parent of Comelineſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which my attempt (howſoeuer done) I haue preſumed vpon hope of full remiſsion for my boldneſſe to dedecate the ſame vnto your worship, although far vnworthy and ouer baſe to be receiued, the which trustinge you will none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe
<pb facs="tcp:19634:6"/> accept than did Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toexerxes the Apple of the poore man, I cloſe vp my matter, humbly beſechinge Almightie God perfectly to guide you in the steps of his moſt holy wil, merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to graffe in you the light of true godlineſſe, ardently to cauſe that Vertuous Lady of yours to burne in the pefect workes of Christianity, abundantly to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plenish you both with much worl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des worſhip, wealth and proſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, and after this tranſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>orie life to inaugure you both with the Bliſfull ioyes of celestiall feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie. Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your dayly Oratour I. C.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="translators_preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:19634:7"/>
            <head>The Preface of the Tranſlatour to the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Erence <hi>the worthy wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> of Comedies, when as he had once ended his works and determined vvith him ſelfe to publiſh the ſame, doubtleſſe he feared nothinge more than the maleuolous reprehencion of carping tounges. For he knevv aſſuredly, that at thoſe daies (as euermore hetherto it hath been) the common people as they polluted their bodies vvith voluptuous and ill fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured manners, ſo did they defile and contami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate their mindes vvith the furious dartes of ZOY<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LVS Spirit. And to ſay the truth, he vvrought him ſelfe this ſuſpicion not vvithout a cauſe: for as ſoone as he had diſcloſed the ſecrettes of his ſtudie vvhich not vvithout great toile and paineful labour hee had vvrapped together, there vvanted not ſome vvho weare redie bente and prepared to be wreake the ſpitefull malice of their cancred hartes, and vvithout iuſt cauſe of controlment to manifeſt the priuie ſtinges of their venemous conſcience. This (gentle Reader) when I conſidered with my felfe, I muſt needes confeſſe that I was greatlie diſmaide, and meruailouſlie terrified from mine enterpriſe, and alreadie, as it were through ſundrie concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to my ſelfe, allured and perſwaded rather to retire, than hardilie and ſtoutlie to aduenture my
<pb facs="tcp:19634:7"/> iourney. Yet contrariwiſe I ponderinge in my minde the contrarietie of humane Nature, and the maruailous diuerſitie of diſpoſicion wherwith it is embrewed, and then againe vnderſtanding that all are not enemies vnto the Crowne of Vertue, ne Foes to the Scepter of Godlineſſe, I thought it more expedient by my ſimple labour and induſtry to gratifie and pleaſe the good, than by ſuppreſſing my attempt cowardlie to flee the buſie braines of the naughtie and reprobate. Certes the wicked are to be abandoned with their wickedneſſe, but the good are to be loued and cheriſhed for their god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe. The ſtudious ſercher of wiſdom will more ſeriouſlie purſue the holſom and neceſſarie inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions for life, then the exquiſite ſituation of words. and will rather couet fruitfull leſſons, and good ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monicions, than ſugred ſentences, oratorial trickes, and outlandiſh termes. But the vnſtedfaſt and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable minde of the vicious perſon (I will ſpeake of a thinge manifeſtlie and commonlie knowne) had leiffer to eſpy ſome friuolous doubte to cauell and Queſtion vpon, than to folow any ſeemelie aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſment, perfectlie ſtaking out the waie to laudable Vertue. Such a Reader as hath his good wil fully addicted to paſtaunces and vnhappie delites had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I dare ſay bothe to ſee and reade the brutiſh bookes of VENVS plaies, than to ſpend his time and buſie his braine in ſuch a Treatiſe which may inſtruct and teache him to liue Prudentlie, iuſtlie, valiauntlie, and ſoberlie: with the honeſt Reader I truſt I ſhall purchaſe fauoure and iuſt commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and to the other this little worke ſhalbe ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient
<pb facs="tcp:19634:8"/> to teache him for to vanquiſh and bridle his vnfauorie delite in bourding, to mittigate his furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous braide of reprehencion, to aſſwage the combe of his inſolente Arrogancie, to appeaſe the rage of his ſkornefull ſpirite, and finallie to make him not onlie a fitte Diſciple or hearer, but alſo a profitable follower of <hi>Morall Philoſophie.</hi> Verelie all eſtates, all degrees, all ages, haue preſently laide be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their Eies to looke on the Glaſſe of all Vertue: for as in a Glaſſe they may eaſelie contemplate what is decent, or els vnſeemely in their parſonage, and apparell, ſo by faſtening their mindes and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandinges herevpon they may with no leſſe fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilitee ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke conſider, and beare away what is to be folowed in their whole courſe of life, or vvhat is to be eſchewed, vvhat to be retained, as good and profitable, or vvhat to be reiected as vnco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modious and hurtefull. Such vvhether they be noble or baſe, riche or poore, old or yong, as haue al their delices, and corporall delites as fleſhfondinges, and paum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peringes of the vitall porcion ſubiecte to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novvned &amp; victorious bondage of REASON, ſuch I ſay haue here to gather aduiſements and inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions profitable and expediente to ratifie and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme their liues: and others vvho like EPICV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RTENS are vanquiſhed vvith gorgious fare and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uervvhelmed, buried, and drovvned, in the bottom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe Gulffes of innumerable vanities, haue hereby to reform their inſeſtuous conuerſacions, to amend their notorious faultes, to baniſh their toubleſome woodes of minde, to expell and put away their ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed doinges, and by adorninge them ſelues
<pb facs="tcp:19634:8"/> with the flouriſhinge Braunches of Vertue by litle and litle to creepe to the Fountaine of that greateſt Soueraintie For aſſure thy ſelfe (gentle Reader) that no man liuing can attaine vnto the vttereſt good (as ARISTOTLE the Prince of al Philoſophers doth ſay) vnleſſe he ſhall firſt ſubdue his apetites, bridell his deſires, Impriſon his luſts, and confound his mad and beſtiall affections, through which nature is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feebled, and he withdrawen from the fellowſhip of goodneſſe and honeſtie. And that I may not bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe thy pacience any lenger, I doo inſtantly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, that if any part of this my Tranſacion ſhall offend thine eares, thou wilt courtouſly deale with me, rather conſidering the proper worthineſſe and ſence of the Aucthor whiche is moſte excellence, then my baſeneſſe and tennitie of Stile, for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fault of Eloquence.</p>
            <trailer>¶ Fare well.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="acrostic_poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:19634:9"/>
            <head>¶ Holſome Counſell for a Chriſtian man.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>G</hi>eue almes to the poore dayly.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>E</hi>ndure affliction quietly.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>R</hi>emember thy end ſtedfastly.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>V</hi>tter Gods word manfully.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I</hi>n all thinges worke rightfully.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>S</hi>erue God and thy Prince duely.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>C</hi>all for grace howerly.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>L</hi>oue thy neighbours freendly.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Y</hi>eld to the truth meekely.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>F</hi>auour learning earnestly.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>T</hi>rust in Christs mercy faithfully.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>O</hi>btaine thou friendship perfectly.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>N</hi>o man oppreſſe Wrongfully.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:19634:9"/>
            <head>Cornelius Valerius his Morall Deſcription lately Engliſſhed.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>Of the ende and Partes of Morall Science. Cap. i.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Thica <hi>Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phia,</hi>
                  </hi> which in Latin is called <hi>De Moribus &amp; Moralis,</hi> the phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophie of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niers &amp; Morall, is a meane to liue well: either a Science to iudge vprightly of conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and of the Actions and duties of common lyfe. The Philoſophers onely imitatyng the light of Nature &amp; Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon as their Guide, haue deliuered it
<pb facs="tcp:19634:10"/> vnto vs dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly adorned: whoſe whole induſtrie eſpecially either is conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaunt in the boultynge out, and vnfoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the perplexitie of Nature, or els in the Doctrine of life and condicions.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>d.</note>Albeit perdy, as <hi>CICERO</hi> writeth, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>continent after a three parted kinde of Philoſophie was receyued of <hi>PLATO:</hi> the one of lyfe and Facions, the other of Naturall and diffuſe things: the third of reaſonyng and adiudgyng both what is true, and what is falſe, what is honeſt in talke, or euill, what is conſonant, what diſagreable: yet they haue pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued no member of Philoſophy more exactly (<hi>SOCRATES</hi> being the Author and Counſellour) than that, than which nothyng was more behoueable to paſſe humaine life delectably, which traineth and faſhioneth the properties of men, and righteth all the operacions of lyfe by the Squire of Vertue: that the way to liue honeſtly may be embraced: that the opinions of men might be vprightly infourmed of commodious and hurtfull things, honeſt &amp; filthy, of matters to be deſired &amp; auoided, of thynges profitable
<pb facs="tcp:19634:10"/> and vnprofitable: who oftentymes ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng Sentence of theſe peruerſly, do preiſe good and euill not accordynge to their valuacion. An vpright iudgement of diuine &amp; humain matters is the very gorgious reward of God For God both reiſing vp the brightneſſe of our minde, &amp; alſo the power of vnderſtandinge dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened through the infectiue ſickneſſe of the body, doth poliſh it with a new light eake redreſſeth our wil through his cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencie earſt piteouſly depraued. Wee being armed with theſe proppes may aſſaie to atchiue vnto the knowledge &amp; intelligence of trouthe. There be ſome who deeme that the beſt proporcion of liuing ought rather to be gathered out of ſacred Scriptures,<note place="margin">VV<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> Phil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phy i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> be m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tated chriſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> men <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> than out of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane Philoſophie: which wee like wiſe would ſuppoſe to be more ſure and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, if thoſe thinges were compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended in thoſe celeſtiall learninges vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred by the mouth of the Omnipotent, which are deſcriued of Ethnical writers touching the Ciuill aſſociacion of men among them ſelues, &amp; the mainteining of the weale publike, without whiche,
<pb facs="tcp:19634:11"/> they who obey the precepts of God, and the holy men are not of power to leade a peaſible life. Wherfore becauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers ignorant verily of Chriſtian Religion, yet very ſtudious of humain wiſdom, imitating that law of Nature engrauen from aboue in all mennes mindes, haue geuen lawes profitable to leade the life vprightly, and right ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent documents concerning maners with a conſtant and perpetual ſentence of iuſt and wrongfull doinges, and haue left vs graue ſayings by which we may be encouraged to Vertue, and terrified from vices, and may vnderſtande that we ought to liue well and honeſtly ſelfe Nature being our leader, eake diſcerne the rewardes whiche are prepared of God for the good, and puniſhmentes for the reprobate, and that conſcience bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring witneſſe, by which euery wight is either accuſed, or excuſed: why ſhould we be afraide to vſe theſe, eſpecially which nothing impugne Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and profite not a little? we ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore borowing of the very beſt Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers the conuenienteſt rules to liue
<pb facs="tcp:19634:11"/> ordinately oughte to meaſure them ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordinge to the precepte of holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. The ſumme of all Philoſophie Morall conſiſteth in theſe three points: that the end of man and felicity may be vnderſtanded, that troubleſome moodes may be aſſwaged, that vertues and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarious to theſe may be diligently con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, that them we may embrace, &amp; eſchew theſe, and may gouerne our life with vertue, godly, and iuſtlie: leſſe we ſhould conceiue a peruerſe opinion of Catholike religion, or leſſe we would charge another with that, which wee would not our ſelues. For that is the chiefeſt regarde of well minded Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers, that the will of men may be ſhaped to vertue, and to all humanity, &amp; amiable concord, that the life may be guided both priuatly and openly, and be obedient vnto the determinacion of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. This diſcipline of life trinely to be inſtituted although it be one, and the ſame notwithſtanding being ſeuered in three partes, after a diuers conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, it is diſtributed into <hi>Monaſticen,</hi> into <hi>Oeconomicen,</hi> and into <hi>Politicen:</hi> that is to
<pb facs="tcp:19634:12"/> wit into ſolitarie, Domeſticall and Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill: of which the firſt apperteineth to faſhion the conditions of ſinguler men: the other to gouerne the Family well: The third rightly to rule the common Wealth. The firſt furniſheth euery mans minde, and allureth it to vertue, and is the ſeedplot of an houſeholde, as the multitude of houſeholds be the fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dacion of a Citie. And firſt and formoſt verely that ſhalbe made appara<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t which bewtifieth the guiſes and minde of eche perſon, with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leſſons of honeſt liuinge. For firſt of all others he is to be lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned who may be able to trade either the family, or els the Citie well. After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes compendiouſly the houſeholde prouidence, eke the politike ſhal be tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, which perhaps it ſhalbe lawfull to comprehend vnder that place of the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litarie member of philoſophy, by which Prudencie is handled, except any one had rather to wreſt it vnto common Iuſtice, that there may be an equitie domeſticall and ciuill. Becauſe then the mattier in which all this Philoſophy of Maners is buſied, are humaine actions,
<pb facs="tcp:19634:12"/> which ſhe teacheth to order diſcretli (for al they are adiected to ſome final ſcope) I thinke it conuenient wee ſay nothing in this place, before that briefly wee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate of the ende and greateſt good, vnto whiche the operations are directed.</p>
               <p>Which beyng vnderſtanded, immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atly wée ſhall diſpute ſomewhat more abundantly of Actions, by which an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traunce may be made vnto that ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raintie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>Of the end of man, and the Soueraine good. Cap. ij.</head>
               <p>ONely men by reaſon they are ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed with knowledge do not onely ſomwhat for ſom end, but alſo purpoſe ſom vtmoſt marke of all theyr labours, &amp; hit moſt commodious for them ſelues: But all other liuing creatures are ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried to that onely which is preſent tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough the blind ſweigh of Nature. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe euery end verily, if it be to be wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed for of a man, is good the latter end ſhalbe the ſoueraine good, and to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired
<pb facs="tcp:19634:13"/> of it ſelfe, for whoſe ſake all things are conſtituted, and through adeption of whiche men are made Fortunate and bleſſed: Yet what maner of thing that is, whiche may ſeeme to be accompted laſt and one alone, eke the greateſt good it is doubted of philoſophers, and a long time inquired for in vayne, and after ſundrye facions called in Queſtion: of which ſom haue placed felicity in plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, others in knowledge, ſom in honor others in other matters. Plato more deuine then the reſt collocated the ſame in vſing the contemplacion of the chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt goodneſſe, either of the good <hi>Idaea</hi> or els of God and heauenly wiſdom: Vnto whom by how much any man may be made more like, by ſo much he thought him more happy, and the rather a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partner of be atitude: But this felicity not to chaunce in this life, becauſe no man may be ſaid happy before his dying day. Ariſtotle in his firſt booke <hi>Ad Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comachum,</hi> eſteemed felicitie to be ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuated in a perfect action anſwerable to perfect vertue, that is to wit whiche may be framed by the rule of wiſdome:
<pb facs="tcp:19634:13"/> becauſe ſhe did appeare to tranſporte very commendable and ſuffycient per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to man: Whereas alſo the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ripatetikes do commonſtrate a bleſſed lyfe to be concluded by vertue: Which yet if it be garnyſhed with the gooddes of body and Fortune, ſhould be moſte bleſſed: for he graunted bleſſedneſſe to conſiſt of a tryple ſort of goods: but in his tenth Booke he dyd ſuppoſe it to be pytched in delectation contemplatiue: that although that actiue felicyty may be referred to thys contemplatiue, yet in her proper kinde ſhe may be the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall end. As who ſay truly, that whiche is one ſoueraine good, may be double.</p>
               <p>Plato more better, and more agreable vnto chriſtian religion, &amp; without doubt more truly did define it thus, that accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge to his opinion alſo a ſoueraintie ſhould be appoynted for vs very co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diouſly,<note place="margin">The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rayn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> for m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> thro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> laſtin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> an eternal pleaſure of ſeynge &amp; hauing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fruition of God, to be wyſhed for of it ſelf: the which who that obtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eth is rightly named bleſſed: who now wanteth nothyng vnto perfect felicity, &amp; ſo deliteth therin, that he may requeſt
<pb facs="tcp:19634:14"/> no whit more, ſith he is diſpatched from all calamities, and enriched with euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtyng life: which no man can compaſſe but through the benefit and gift of god, leſſe any one ſhould glory in his owne opinion. For that is not of him that is willyng, nor yet purueying, but of God hauyng compaſſyon, and the peculiar dowry of the Holy Ghoſte graunted through Chriſt our Lorde: vnto whom no man can attaine, vnleſſe the heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly father ſhall draw him, the Author of all felicity, in whome, knowne by the Sonne, the confidence of immortality is repoſed for vs: whiche are borne for no other intent, then that we ſhould ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge him to be the builder, that we ſhould attribute all glory vnto him, that wee ſhoulde loue him with all our mynde, and ſhoulde worſhip him as he hath geuen in commaundement. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe wee muſt paſſe vnto this marke by the operacions of vertue, it foloweth that firſt of all wee reaſon of theſe. But where as the Actions are voluntary, and good wyll it ſelfe is ingraſſed in the mynde of man, which beyng ſubiect to
<pb facs="tcp:19634:14"/> God only hath a free originall of doyng, but is ſo diſturbed with diuers mocions that humane operacions moſt comonly do roue from the ſtreight pathe of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue: Wee wil in few wordes compriſe the beginnyng of affections, and of vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and vertues. The ſoule of man loc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked in a mortal corps is as it were ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred in two partes, of which one is hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly, like a certayne beame gliſtering with diuine excellency, as the minde.</p>
               <p>The other is yoked to the body, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>etite, or deſier, and anger. The higher <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s a receauer of Reaſon: The lower is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gnorant: it is hir parte to rule, and it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>elonges vnto this to obey. But this oftentimes as an Horſe waryng fierſe, not regarding the will of the Carter, is whirled w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a violent brayde vnto thoſe thinges which him liketh, whether they be honeſt or filthy, yeldyng a deafe eare to reaſon, and not hearyng the mynde and intelligence, whiche is a copartner of thoſe knowledges, whiche by nature are planted in vs, or rather ingendred of God: and at all times incourageth vnto honeſt mattiers, whether they be
<pb facs="tcp:19634:15"/> pleaſant, or lamentable. For there is a triple good: Honeſt, profitable, and pleaſaunt. Honeſt is, which agreeth with the ſtreight ſentence of Reaſon: Profitable is, which ſuccoureth nature and lyfe. Pleaſaunt is, which deliteth naturall appetite, as the drynke the thyrſty. And out of theſe Fountaynes procede all actions. It is the duety of the minde and Intelligence to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myne: but to the other parte it belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth to execute the commaundement of the minde, and to labour. The minde hath two principall Intelligences en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talied of nature: the one of debatinge truth and falſhoode, the other of diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning good and euill. For al men through a certaine ſecret ſence do diſcerne what thinges are iuſt, and wrongfull (ſo that this light of nature be not peſterd) for nature hath geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to vs as it were litle ſparkes and ſeedes, and a certayne pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cliuitie of minde, and facultie to labour. This affection doth ſtirre: Operacion ſucceedeth the affection, and by often o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peracions there is gotten a perfectnes, either of vertue, if it be trayned vnto a
<pb facs="tcp:19634:15"/> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ood end, or els of vice, if vnto an euill. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd this is the grounde of all humaine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ctions.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>Of Affections. Cap. iij.</head>
               <p>SIth perdie euery fourme of vertues and vices doth ſpring as it were out <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f theſe Fountaines, hability, affection, operation, and perfection: we wil com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendiouſly manifeſt theſe: And certes thoſe few things which are ſaid concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning faculty ſhall ſuffice. And let that difference be obſerued betwixt the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue readines of the minde, &amp; the braide or affection of this procliuity. As choler doth moue the nature of an ireful man, ſo dooth the coueting of glory force the couetous of honour. Henceforth then we haue to breake our minde of affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Affection, is a commocion of the minde, diſquieting the tranquility ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, which in Greeke is called <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and of Cicero <hi>Perturbatio,</hi> a Perturba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and it is defined, a troubleſom and a viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t moode of the ſoule, bended from
<pb facs="tcp:19634:16"/> reaſon, an enemye to the minde, and quiet life. The Stoikes when as they ſaw a man to be turmoyled hither and thither with many and wicked deſires, and falſly ſuppoſed the very nature of man to be vncorrupted, and not deflou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, dthey gainſaid affections to be natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, but graunted them to be only opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions eyther of good or yll, and in theyr kinde euery one to be vicious, and to be rooted out of the nature of menne, from which they would a wiſe man to be fre: yet they are eaſily conuicted of errour. For firſt of al that they are Natiue and ingendred, by y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is lightly confirmed, becauſe motions and certayne inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are ingraffed in liuyng creatures by nature, as the Zeale of parentes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes theyr Children. And who ſeeth not ſom men to be more enclined to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger or loue, to ioyfulneſſe or heauineſſe than other ſom. Farthermore that all are not faultye thereby it is apparant inough, by reaſon the very law of God geueth vs in charge to beare loue to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde him, towarde all men, towardes our wife, children, and parentes: And
<pb facs="tcp:19634:16"/> enioyneth vs mercy, hope, confidence, ioye, and ſome other affections very profitable and expedient to encourage the minde. For what is more commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious for the life of man than the hope of glory, and rewardes, and the feare of rebuke and puniſhments. And ſo doubt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les affctions may be handſomly diuided that ſom may be called good by nature, which agre with reaſon or els with the preſcript of nature, as good will, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion. Some euill, which do diſagrée, as Hatred, Enuy, Pride, Diſpere. Som betwixt bothe, as anger, hope, boldnes, feare, deſire, loue, merineſſe, ſorow: which that they may not ſwarue from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ertue, they are to be ruled by the bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ell of reaſon, and to be Iudged by me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diocrity. But neither is that to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended, which ſom conſtrued, that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections are naturall, not alſo volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. For whereas our will onely ſubiect to God may apppeare to haue a free O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginall to worke, it is to be thought, the very redineſſe perdie vnto theſe or them, and likewiſe the firſt motion to be naturall; but theyr vexacions to be
<pb facs="tcp:19634:17"/> voluntary, and able to be chaſtiſed by th'authority of reaſon, leſſe they ſhould run headling, and be plucked with vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, eake inforce a man immediatly welny vnwillyng vnto naughtineſſe. Albeit truly at that time the will coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting doth range at liberty, and by ſome meanes may reteine it if ſo ſhe woulde inuocate God the helper. For put caſe it be feeble, yet there is ſome libertie whiche when ſhame &amp; feare are ſet out to the ſhow may be of power to bridle the affections. And that they can be cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected by diſcipline, thoſe wordes deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered of God do manifeſtlie denounce. <hi>Sub te erit appetitus tuus, &amp; tu Dominaberis illi:</hi> Vnder thee ſhalbe thine apetite, &amp; thou ſhalt beare rule ouer it. Wheras alſo a man conſiſteth of two partes, a Soule and a bodie, and there is a double force of the ſoule, one a copartner of reaſon, the other void: ſhe is ſtedfaſt and quiet, this wandring, and tormented with af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, whiche moſte commonly doth diſquiet her: where by it inſueth that a man, if he doth purſue the aduiſe of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and intelligence he may want per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbacion:
<pb facs="tcp:19634:17"/> But if he had rather to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Subiecte vnto the concupiſcence of the body, he may be diuerſlie prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked. The Fountaine then of affections is that part of the Soule voide of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: and that is double <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng angry, and <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>very deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous of a thinge. The which if refuſinge the Empire and Yoke of the minde and reaſon, it be caried with his proper ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemencie, it is needefull that forthwith one or other of the perturbations bee incenſed, and plucked throughe the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion or ſimilytude of good or yll, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times bither and ſomtimes thither, eke nowe and then be broughte all oute of frame with pleaſure or luſte, and one while with timidity or hatred. For vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to theſe twoo ſortes it appeareth that any one of the affections may be refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, becauſe all mocions proceede from a ſuſpicion of good or euill, whether it be preſent, or abſent. Out of the Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of good floweth pleaſure, and out of the conceit of euill commeth ſorow. Vnto pleaſure are referred, loue, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, gladneſſe, whiche ſuccoure nature,
<pb facs="tcp:19634:18"/> and among theſe eſpeciallie ioy: Vnto ſorow appertaine, anger, hatred, feare, ſadneſſe, which diſcommoditie Nature moſt painfully. The Harbourough for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſouthe of them all is featelie diſpoſed in the harte, to whom there is a greate familyarity with will, whiche either may couet, or els eſchew, if any thing be obiected, whiche may ſeem either to pleaſure, or domage nature.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>Of Loue. Cap. iiij.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Oue is an inclination of will, prone to that which is thought good. For when as any thinge is profered, which either is good in deede, or els de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liteth with a certain likelyhood of good, through that opinion, the greedy faculti of the Soule is vehemently inticed to enioy and poſſeſſe the ſame. And of the goods, which are ſought for of men, we tolde that there were three kindes: Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, Profitable and Pleaſant, whiche
<pb facs="tcp:19634:18"/> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly are coupled together, becauſe one thyng both may be honeſt, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable, and pleaſant: yet not by and by that which is either profitable, or plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant, is honeſt: whereas theſe now and than may appere to contende with ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtie. But for all this nothinge is in deed either profitable, or pleaſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, which ſame is not honeſt. Certes what is honeſt that is onely required for the proper behoofe, no conſideration had neither of commoditie, nor of delecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. How greate the power of loue is, the verſes of Poets do beare witneſſe, and wee deeme that there be very few whiche can quite them ſelues cleare of all loue. Plato conſtituted a threefolde loue, the firſt which embraceth and che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſheth only Vertue, but this is exemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from the number of affections, he appeareth rather to be reckned among vertues, becauſe he vſeth the iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of vpright Reaſon: The other filthie which cloueth to the pleaſure of bodie: The thyrde whiche mindeth the Soule and Body. Nothyng is more noble than the firſt, nothynge more foule than the
<pb facs="tcp:19634:19"/> other: The thyrd truly is a companion of bothe, but yet he rometh abrode no leſſe than the other: By reaſon he reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renceth the perſonage of the body, and ardenly eſteemeth it. Vnleſſe wee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pine this loue reſortyng amorouſly, and ſtrokyng the minde with ſugred words and except this loue ſike ſoule brought vnto another bayte: Feates of Phiſick ſhould be practiſed in vayne, when as now the loue ſhall growe in vſe, eake ſhal haue taken deeper rootes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>Of Deſire and Hope. Cap. v.</head>
               <p>DEſire is a luſte to enioye that good, whiche as yet is not preſente: If ſo that be in place, it is loued, but if it bee out of ſight, it is coueited. Out of this Fountain (if the ſentence of reaſon be neglected, and the deſire bee immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, and excéede the boundes and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits of Nature who is apaid with few thinges) many vices do ariſe: as Nig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardlines, Ambicion, Senſualitie, Riot &amp; ſuch other. Hope is defined of Cicero,
<pb facs="tcp:19634:19"/> an expectation of good, to whom diſpaire is contrarye, a ſuppoſed difficultye and miſtruſt of a good thinge to be atchiued, the which ſhalbe Recapitulated heare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after among the fourmes of ſadneſſe.</p>
               <p>It is the guiſe of a wiſe man, to hope for thoſe thinges, whiche he maye attaine, neither raſhly to diſpaire, whither he may atchiue through trauaile. And this hope verely by which we wiſh for good, either trewe or ſhadowed, differeth from that whiche is tearmed Theologi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, and it is a vertue, eke is depainted to be a waytinge for eternall felicitie: Vnto whom in like caſe the repugnant vice is, <hi>Deſperatio,</hi> deſpeire.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>Of Gladneſse. Cap. vi.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Ladneſſe is an affection which is ſtirred with the opinion of ſome preſent goodneſſe, wherwith the minde is delited. Cicero doth diſtynguiſh <hi>Gaudiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> and <hi>Laetitiam,</hi> ioye and gladneſſe in this wiſe, that the
<pb facs="tcp:19634:20"/> minde ſhould be mooued with ioy paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently, and conſtantly, but with glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe vainely and prodigally. With this affection y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Nature is merueilouſly delighted, and the hert enlarged, and as it were embracynge that whiche is apparant good, doth ſtirre the minde ſweetly and delectably, and fauſtreth life in the hert, whiche ſorow the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie paſſion, doth oppreſſe. And this pleaſantneſſe and delectacion for the amplitude of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good which is propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, may be greater or leſſer, and either honeſt or filthy. It ſhabe honeſt if it be anſwerable to the meane of nature, and vnto reaſon: what one is gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> through the contemplation and ſtudies of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable thinges. But filthy if it be immoderate, and diſſonant to reaſon: what one is receiued of corporal delites of peruerſe exerciſes, and of yll will: as if any man ſhould be delited with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mans harme, than which vice no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ought to be more abrogate from a man, eſpecially a Chriſtian.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:19634:20"/>
               <head>Of Hatred and anger and like affections. Cap. vij.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ontrarye to Loue is ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred: which is defined of Cicero, <hi>Ira inueterata,</hi> a longe feſtred Anger, that is to wit of longe conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance. This affection is ingendred of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diſcontenting of the minde, deteſtinge the harme which is vnderſtanded, &amp; da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maged either with the deede or ſayinge of ſom man, or deming him ſelfe hurted: and ſometimes abhorring from ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers freendſhip through a priuy inſtinct of nature. Euen as perdie by Loue all all men are accorded, ſo by hatred they are vnyoked, than whiche nothynge is more pernicious to humaine ſocietie, which alſo by ſo much is more irkeſom, by how much more ſecretly it inuadeth. To contempne vices it profiteth but to loue a man Chriſtian charitie commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, and to forgeue him whiche offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth: But to hate a man for no cauſe, is very obſurde, and moſt diſſonant from
<pb facs="tcp:19634:21"/> vpright iudgement. Vnto hatred are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed many affection whiche are to be auoyded of a godly man: As diſpight, as anger, as Hoſtilitie. Deſpight whereby any man thinketh another more baſe then himſelfe: Whereas truly there is no cauſe why any one ſhoulde ſuppoſe himſelfe to be preferred before his fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, by reaſon that he cannot common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate any thinge of himſelfe, whiche he hath not receiued els where, as it ought to be moſt euident vnto the Chriſtians by holy Scriptures. Anger is defined, a luſt to puniſh him who may ſeeme to haue hurted with iniury. This affection appeareth to be mingled with ſorowe and a greedineſſe of reuengeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, which greeuouſly racketh a man, and ſharpely kindleth agaynſt him, of whome he is thought to be diſpleaſured, the moſte troubleſome of all the affections: by which not only the minde, but alſo the whole body is brought into ſuche a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexitie that for anger a man can vneth ſee, and moderate his ſenſes, and ſcarce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpeake. Hereto doth Hoſtilitie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longe, which is defined an anger of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing
<pb facs="tcp:19634:21"/> obſeruynge oportunitie. And hither diſcorde the deſtruction of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon weale, and hither all hatred is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred. <hi>Iracundia</hi> doth differ from <hi>Ira,</hi> becauſe <hi>Iracundia</hi> is a natiue faculty, by which any man is made prone to anger But <hi>Ira</hi> is a commocion of this vertue, and a rage bended from reaſon: Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by now and than the minde is ſo tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moyled, that the angrie man doth very litle diſagree from the Frantike. And truly it may be verified of Horace, <hi>Ira fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>or breuis,</hi> anger is a ſhorte furie: and of Ennius, <hi>Inſaniae principium,</hi> the originall of Madneſſe. The bloud is incenſed with this paſſyon, and waxeth hotte in the bodie, and the Spirites ſodenly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieted doo ſo trouble a man, and cauſe him ſo vnagreable to him ſelfe, that he is ſayd to be out of his Wittes, neither to become his owne man before that the hot brayned moode ſhall aſſwage, and the vehemencie relinquiſht. But not euery anger is lyke contentious: for one is eaſier, eake ſooner prouoked, and haleth a man vnwares, but abideth not longe: Another is more gentell
<pb facs="tcp:19634:22"/> truly, yet more bitter, and of greater induraunce, and cleuyng to hatred, and ſeekyng auengement. Neither ought euery anger appere vicious, ſithe in ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Scriptures wee may reade in this wiſe: <hi>Iraſcimini, &amp; nollite peccare:</hi> Become you angrie and ſinne not. Neither vncommodiouſly of Ariſtotle the mediocritie of anger betwixt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe and defect is renowned, and mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate anger linked as a companion of worthy proweſſe vnto fortitude, which the auncient Academikes (Cicero bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring record) reported to be as it weare the Whetſtone of valiaunt courage, that is to witte, the aſſiſtaunte: which Seneca geueth in precept to vſe, not as a Capitain but as a ſouldiar. We muſt then be agréeued with vngodlineſſe, wronge, and other vices: and our mind muſt be aduaunced when nede is, when time and place do require, but reſt raig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, if no ſuch occaſion be miniſtred of anger. And by how much more gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſly the minde is ſolicitated, by ſo much more painfully we ſhall brydle Choler, wee ſhall maiſter the brayde,
<pb facs="tcp:19634:22"/> and with all meane and might ſhall op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe it forthwith the dominion of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon reuoked, and that diſmounted which kendled the wrath, we ſhall extinguiſh the feruency, or els the puniſhment dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred till another ſeaſon, we ſhall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenuate the paſſion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>Of Sadneſſe. Cap. viij.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Adneſſe, or hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uineſſe, is a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbacion, draw<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>inge together &amp; oppreſſynge the minde, which is defined of <hi>Cicero,</hi> a freſhe opinion of preſent euill, wherupon it may ſeem leifull the mind to be enlarged, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted. And after a bréefer way. Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uineſſe is a ſhrincking of the minde rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon repining. This taketh beginninge through the contemplacion of ſom euil, or els through the wante of ſome good thing. From this Fountaine proceede
<pb facs="tcp:19634:23"/> ſundry paſſions which Cicero numbreth in the end of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> third booke of Tuſculans Queſtions, and in the fourth, when as he had conſtituted foure ſortes of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbacions, &amp; had explaned them, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compteth them beyng reckned in theſe words: But vnto ech diſturbance more partes of the ſame ſecte are adiected, as vnto ſadneſſe, enuy, emulation, backbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, compaſſion (but this we ſuppoſe to be a good affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, not a greef of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mind) vexacion, wailing, ſorow, infelicity, wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, lamentacion, penſiueneſſe, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quietneſſe, affliction, diſpeire, of which belowe we ſhall debate, and if any moe be of the ſame ſtocke. Hitherto Cicero, whom reade you your ſelfe defining e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery of the fourmes. As euery pleaſure is not ſaide to be vicyous, ſo neither e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery ſadneſſe. And as it is a laudable thinge to triumphe at vertue: ſo to be ſorrowfull for vice, to reſtreigne the minde immoderatly deliting, is profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: neither ſemeth it an vnhoneſte thing meaſurably to bewaile our wiues children, or Parentes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:19634:23"/>
               <head>Of Feare. Cap. ix.</head>
               <p>FEare is a wayting of euill, either a carefull remembraunce of penſiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe about to enſew, as Cicero re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordeth, and it is repugnant to hope.</p>
               <p>Feare is ingendred of the haling togea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the hart throughe an opinion of imminent perill. Moderate feare is profitable, aſſenting to the counſaile of reaſon: But the vnmeaſurable or ouer ſmall is diſcommended. Som are more timorous, ſome more bolde, which the Phiſicions déeme to be attributed to the Complexion of body: but yet in this place their Iudgemente is of no ſimple importaunce, by which timidity either is increaſed, or diminiſhed. This per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbacion doth very ſore diſprofite Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and cheefely ſo tormenteth a man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n ſodaine caſes, that who is horribly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtoniſhed may appeare no leſſe to fall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t of his right wittes, than he which is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reeuouſly diſpleaſed. Vnder feare be many fourmes comprehended, of which all there is one cauſe; the ende perdie
<pb facs="tcp:19634:24"/> and opinion of euil is diuerſe: Slouth, terrour, ſhame, feare, quaking, diſmai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng, trouble, dreade, whoſe definitions you ſhall eftſones finde with Cicero in the ſame fourthe booke of Tuſculans queſtions. To theſe béen adioyned flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie, whiche alſo is termed Timorous inticement: Suſpicion a feare through a conſideracion of miſchiefe at hande: diſpeyre a low abaſhement of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> minde: Penſiueneſſe a prickinge care through the expectation of euill, and ſome other mo fourmes. Cicero hath deſcriued ſhame, and hath not defined it. The de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finicion may be abſolued, that ſhame may be a feare of diſhoneſty, whome bluſhing doth follow, wherof hereafter we will debate more at large in Chapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Sober moode.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>Of Boldneſſe. Cap. x.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Oldeneſſe is gaged a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt feare, that we may in this place vnderſtand a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate vertu of aduenturing
<pb facs="tcp:19634:24"/> and a confidence of the mind, &amp; a certain mediocrity betwixt to much and to litle either betweene timiditie and vnmea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurable hope, by which any one neither dreadyng miſchief like to chaunce, nor preſent, doth aduenturouſly icoperde his ioynctes. This is engendred other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe than feare, through the extending of the harte, the Spirites augmenting the heat therof: through whoſe force by reaſon that the mind is gouerned more often than by reaſon and counſell, the appellacion of boldnes is welme taken in the worſe parte. It is diſagreeable vnto true Fortitude, which when as prudently the daunger is throughly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined aduentureth the ſame with a manly courage. And doubtleſſe hether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to of affections: whoſe moderation is verye requiſite for ſuch as contende to the wiſhed end by vertues, that alſo we may enioye a certaine tranquilitye of minde in the Earth which in Greeke is called <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, whiche Democritus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined the bound of good thinges, and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>igure and ſemblaunce of that vnfained Beatitude to come: The which with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb facs="tcp:19634:25"/> the benefite of Chriſt, who only is of power to appeaſe the moodes of men through the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fidence of life which ſhall happen, no wight at any ſeaſon hath obteined.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>Of Vertue and her diuiſion and Originall. Cap. xi.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Nto the ende pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning all the actions of menne are direc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: to the whiche they aſpire vertue beinge the guide, which very breefely may be defined.</p>
               <p>A perfection by which the will is pric<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked to do agreably to right reaſon. For vnder the appellacion of right reaſon we vnderſtand the law of Nature, and the knowledges of thoſe thinges which are ingendred with vs, and ingraffed from aboue in our minds, that we may iuſtly determine of things good and bad,
<pb facs="tcp:19634:25"/> honeſt and filthy: as, that God is to bée worſhipped, that no man is to be hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and ſuch like, the whiche ſhall gaily be called the Squire of vertue, vnto whiche the operation of the whole life may be directed: with whom leſſe it doth conſente it can not be nominated a vertue. Vertue is defined of Saint Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine, <hi>Ars bene re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>eque viuendi:</hi> A ſcience to liue well and perfectly. Of Cicero it is termed ſomtimes <hi>Recta ratio,</hi> a right reaſon, ſometimes <hi>Animi Habitus,</hi> a cuſtome of the minde, aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable vnto humane nature, meane, and reaſon: ſometimes <hi>Affectio animi conſtans conueniensque</hi> a ſtedfaſt and a conuenient affection, of the mind, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinge them commendable in whome it perſiſteth. But of Ariſtotle it is defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Habitus animi iudicio ſuſceptus in mediocritate poſitus,</hi> A cuſtome of the minde enterpriſed through reaſon ſitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated in mediocritie. In theſe definitions this worde <hi>Conſtans</hi> expoundeth what manner of thinge <hi>Habitus</hi> is, that wee vnderſtand him to be procured through
<pb facs="tcp:19634:26"/> vſe, and exerciſe. That it is ſaide, <hi>Rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one ſuſceptus,</hi> enterpriſed, or receiued through reaſon, that is to wit through election or aduiſe: that ſignifieth that the operation of vertue is voluntarie. That it is called <hi>Habitus animi,</hi> a cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom of the minde, that doth common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate the habitacle of vertue. That it is, in <hi>mediocritate poſitus,</hi> placed in a competent degree, that is expreſſed in theſe wordes of Horace.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>¶ Vertue is a meane in middes degree</l>
                  <l>Cloſde in both ſides as thou mayſt ſee.</l>
               </q>
               <p>That we may conceiue all vertues to be made moderated by a certaine mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurable rate, which ſhould be approued of wiſe perſons, and ſkilfull in many ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and good. But when we affirme that the operacion of vertue is volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, either taken in hande through a frée Iudgement: that is to be conſidered, that we being furthered by the ſecret benefite of God, and ſuccoure of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſte, withoute whom wée are of ſtrength to worke nothing, obaying the right ſentence of the minde, indeuoring with voluntarie will, may procure the
<pb facs="tcp:19634:26"/> perfection of vertue through diligence and frequent vſe. For theſe be the two principall efficient cauſes of vertue, a minde iudgyng rightly, and a will obei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng him which iudgeth and commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not amiſſe: Whiche yet are very much ſuccoured through learnynge, the which may make brightſom the vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandynge of thoſe ſentences, who are within vs by nature, and the light geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God oftentimes obſcured throughe wonderfull darkeneſſe, as the booke of holy Scripture conteining the .x. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundementes, and through an encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragyng of natiue procliuitie, &amp; through Diſcipline or obſeruacion of manners, and peinfulneſſe in gouernynge opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions, as the ſhu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ning of Idleneſſe, and of theſe thinges which miniſter an occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of offending. Plato writeth in his booke <hi>Meno,</hi> vertue to be geuen of God, not to be ingendred in vs of nature (as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Stoikes</hi> would) neither to conſiſt only by prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, as the Peripatetikes reported.</p>
               <p>Certes it is to bee thought that true vertues do not chaunce vnleſſe through a celeſtiall benefite:<note place="margin">True ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> is the b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fite of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> that alſo there be
<pb facs="tcp:19634:27"/> other ſome with leſſe peines to be mol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified of nature, notwithſtandinge to be ratified by reaſon and cuſtome.</p>
               <p>Touchynge viciouſneſſe there is no doubte that it is voluntarie. Very aptly then it ſeemeth to be graunted that hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine operations are without compul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and that all vertues and vices are voluntary. For what is done by coac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that meriteth neither prayſe, nor diſprayſe: but is eſteemed worthy of forgeueneſſe. Vertue is ſundred of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers into two partes: Iuſtice &amp; For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, and of others into un Prudence Iuſtice, Fortitude, and Temperaunce. Some ſuppoſe vertue, as the whole to conſiſt of members, whiche beynge ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to ſundry actions, may be of ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficacie to conſtitute diuers fourmes, whereas of all, one perfect vertue may be abſolued: neither is there any one of them foure vertues whiche may want the felowſhip of the reſidew. Ariſtotle in only prudencie ſupporteth all ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues to be knitted together. Wee ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prouynge the diuiſion of olde Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers, will diſtribute vertue into them
<pb facs="tcp:19634:27"/> foure braunces, whiche euen now wee haue placed: of whom the firſt doth go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne the intelligence, the reſt the wil: to which may be annected whatſoeuer vertue els where may be traced out. And firſt and formoſt we will miniſter talke of Prudencie, in whoſe reherſall alſo Domeſtical and Politique affaires ſhall compendiouſlye be remembred, which hereafter (if we ſhal thinke good) ſhall be debated more at large. Plato of theſe foure vertues, doth name ſome perfecte, who haue fired there reſtynge places in the minde: of whiche ſuche is the ſocietie emonge them, that one be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing taken away, all do fall vnto corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: but ſome vnperfecte, of which cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, others being exempted, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandinge maye bee able to remaine. Ther is an other particion of Vertues, by which they are diuided, into politike, Purgatory, and of the ſoule clenſed, and into them as are like Paternes, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples: which Macrobius dooth copi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly depainte in the eight Chapiter of his former booke of Commentaries on the dreame of Scipio. The firſte Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb facs="tcp:19634:28"/> teacheth in his Prouerbs, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers wee reade in Eccleſiaſtes, the third in the Ballets, the fourth in God. The politique do rule humayn life, eke maintayne the outward ſociety of life: The Purgatory doo ſcoure the ſpots of the ſoules, and do contend vnto victory. But the vertues of the ſoule clenſed are collocated in him, which (the vices now quite troden vnder foote) doth conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perſeuer in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> loue of vertues: which S. Auguſtine, when as he confirmed the other three, did not alow. They are commonly termed <hi>Exemplares paterus</hi> and examples, which are as it were <hi>Ideae</hi> (as the Greekes do call them) or els fourms and figures in the diuine mind, ſith God is the counterpaine of all good thinges. Vertue is defined of Cicero, as it is declared, ſomtimes <hi>Recta racio</hi> a right reaſon, ſomtimes <hi>Natura in ſe perfecta, &amp; ad ſumum perducta,</hi> a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſounde in it ſelfe, and brought vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the vtmoſt: Otherwhiles <hi>Rationis perfectio,</hi> a perfection of reaſon, which definition Seneca imitatinge, doth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> recorde: Vertue is none other than
<pb facs="tcp:19634:28"/> an vpright reaſon, vnto which as a rule all the doinges of life are directed. And feately euery Originall of vertue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth from perfect reaſon, neither is vertue any other thing, then (as Cicero minionly deſcriueth) a right affection of the minde, from whom as it were from ſom Fountaine all vndefyled operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which are nominated dewties, do proceede, of which Cicero hath excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently written. And thus I ſuppoſe it bee vnderſtanded (becauſe manie haue affirmed that ther is one onely vertue) that perdie there is one office either an action appointed to euery man of vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righte reaſon, which (accordinge to the multiplicity of the mater which it hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth, inclined to ſundrie affayres,) may procreat theſe foure vertues, which we haue remembred aboue. For ther is in very déede, onely one perfect affection of the minde, the mother of all vertues: whoſe chaungeable appellations bee, Prudence, Iuſtice, Fortitude, Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peraunce, of whiche wee will reaſon in order: if firſt wee ſhall géeue this in Leſſon, not onely theſe whiche are
<pb facs="tcp:19634:29"/> called the giftes of the holy Ghoſte, but likewiſe all true vertues (as Plato deuoutely ſuppoſed in that Dialogue which I haue recited afore) to chaunce vnto vs by no meanes, vnles by an hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly benefite: vndoubtedly if we em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the goodneſſes of God, and labour to attaine to the ende, hee beinge oure guide.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>Of Prudencie. Cap. xij.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Rudencie, as it weare the Maiſtreſſe and iudge of other vertues, of which none can be deſtitute, is fitly placed in the firſt degree, as the Capitaine of opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions, and the ſcience of liuing: which is defined of Cicero, the experience of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring, and eſchewinge thinges: that is to wit a right affection of the minde, by which it is perceiued what is to be done or ſhunned in humayn actions. Of <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificius</hi> in bookes of Rhetorik vnto <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rennius,</hi> it is termed <hi>Calliditas</hi> a ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ines, which through a certaine reaſon maye
<pb facs="tcp:19634:29"/> obtaine a choiſe both of good and badde, becauſe all the facultie of wiſdom is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rooued in the election of good and euill <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ings, &amp; of them as be neither good nor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ll. He vnderſtandeth a wilyneſſe, not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> vicious, who oft times boroweth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſame appellacion, but that ſubtility <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch priuyly vndermineth with a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne honeſt, and profitable diſſimula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n. Vnto the which, craftie ſayinges, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d deceiptfull doynges, which in war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> are called Stratagemes, are refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Of the ſame writer alſo prudencie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ermed <hi>Multarum rerum memoria,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> memory of many matters, and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of plentifull affaires. Although per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſdom as other vertues, is conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nte in humaine actions. Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nding eſpecially trouth is Subiecte <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erto, as the mattier, which it hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h. And certes the inquiſicion and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arche of ſoothe, ſeemeth to be peculiar <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> man. Vnto the out finding of veritie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ue vertues comprehended vnder In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>elligence are adioygned of Ariſtotle: Science, Arte, Prudence, Sapience, vnderſtanding of which, Science, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pience
<pb facs="tcp:19634:30"/> and vnderſtandynge require a a definite knowledge, cake an abſolute vertue: Art and prudencie a probable one. Science is defined, a ſure and an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed knowledge and learninge of ſome matter through the cauſe, whiche is perceaued withoute any ayde by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall motions of the minde, or els it is atchiued through demonſtration of ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gumentes: and it is of thoſe thinges whiche may not otherwiſe exiſt, or els be tranſfigured, as diuinity. Arte is ſaid a perfection to diſpatche thoſe things by reaſon which otherwiſe may be: as all humaine craftes. Prudency is defined, A qualitie to perfourme thoſe thinges by reaſon which are either commodious or hurtfull to man. Sapience verely, is a moſt exquiſit knowledge of thoſe mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, whiche are able to bee learned of man, who compriſeth the experience of diuine and human affaires. Vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding is called a qualitie, perceauing the principles, out of which confirmations are deducted. Vnto Prudency he annec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Art, Science, Intelligence and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pience; that althoughe verely he gaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaieth
<pb facs="tcp:19634:30"/> Vertue to be a Science, yet he ſuppoſeth that ſhee is not of power to perſeuer without this. For althoughe onely goodneſſe is purpoſed to vertues, and trouth vnto Diſciplines: yet wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as to the ſearche hereof a greedineſſe of good is coupled. Science, Sapience, Art, and Intelligence, appere that they may not abſurdely be nominated vertues, if they ſerue for the operations of Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, &amp; ſuccoure the outfindinge of that which is good. They ought not attende verelye to the contemplacion of cauſes only, ſithens all the commendacion of Vertue conſiſteth in dooinge, and in go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerning the life vndefiledly. Prudency then may take vnto her as waytynge mates, vnderſtanding, for to know mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters: Science truly to conceiue them: Arte for the generall vſe of life: Sapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence for the out tracting of diuers things that by theſe props ſhe may paſſe to the knowledge of trouth, and may compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend the verie Soueraine good, and the liuely Fountaine of all wiſdome flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with Heauenly waters, &amp; ruſhinge forth moſte ſwiftly into eternall lyfe.
<pb facs="tcp:19634:31"/> Now wheras vnto euery vertu certain ſeats in the ſoule, from whence they iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue, are attributed: A place is graunted to Prudencie in the minde, to the rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunt in the will: ſith it belongeth to prudencie to bolt out what is honeſt, or wicked in matters to be handled and to debate of the ſame with iuſtful ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. Which thyng doubtleſſe is adepted not only by wit, although ſharpe, but by a greate knowledge of ſundry matters. And very pretely it is ſayd, <hi>Longo pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentia ſurgit ab vſu,</hi> Prudence ariſeth through longe practiſe: that we vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the perfection of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> minde, whence creepeth this dexteritie of triynge out the truth, to be termed prudencie, who deſireth a longe life, and the handlynge, and memory of diuers matters, and the ſcience of preſent caſes to leuel vpright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the interchaungeable operation of men. Moreouer it is requiſite that a prudent man be poliſhed with a certain natiue faculty of through ſeyng and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudgyng the trouth: by whiche he may contemplate thinges preſent, and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently diſcuſſe them, may call to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance
<pb facs="tcp:19634:31"/> matters paſt, &amp; may fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee ſequels: through whiche he may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell in takyng aduiſe, and in outfindyng wittily: through which he may paſſe in perceauyng clerely what is true in ech matter, and what is to be attempted: through which he may floriſh in propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinge ſentence iuſtfully, eake in ratifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng ſubtely and wiſyly what is decent, what filthie, what profitable. For there are three partes conteined vnder wyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> a facultie of miniſtrynge holſom counſell, good aduiſe: <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a perfect ſight and cunnyng in finiſhinge of that whiche is excogitated through profitable counſell: and <hi>Gnome,</hi> a ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence and iuſt verdit of matters to bée perfourmed, and a ſtedfaſtneſſe in that which is leyfull. It is the duty than of a prudente wighte (that I may driue my tale at his marke in few wordes) to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member thoſe thinges which are paſt, to be ſkilfull in many matters, to flowe in counſell, to be quicke witted, and to Iudge well: and farthermore to leade not only an vndefiled conuerſacion, but alſo, as place and oportunity in this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb facs="tcp:19634:32"/> life ſhall craue, to becom ſomwhat more charie and circumſpecte. And tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly concerning the charge of Prudencie, who ſhould be kept in humain operaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, we haue treated hitherto. And by reaſon the variety of doinges appertei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to men is ſeuored in three ſortes, that ſome ſhould be of peculiar perſons, which be Coincident to euerie one, and generall: ſom Domeſtical, which ſerue to the order of Family: others ciuill which we muſte put in vre, for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruacion of the Publike fellowſhip of menne: a three parted force of wiſdome likewiſe may be gathered: the one com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to all ſortes, which is named <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſtica</hi> ſolitary, the ſecond <hi>Oeconomica</hi> belongyng to houſeholde: the third <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litica,</hi> which is thought to be the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenteſt of all others, becauſe firſt and formoſt it is buſied in common vtilitie, vnto whiche yet wee muſt clime by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree. For he ſhall not well gouerne ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a family or els a weale publike, who is not a good man, and informed with the rules of condicions and faſhio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnto euery vertue, and ſhall come
<pb facs="tcp:19634:32"/> prepared to the common wealth, and ſhall wit perfectly to nurtur an houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde. The two latter of theſe three members of Morall Philoſophie: Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they be ſeuerally debated of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtotle, yet in this place likewiſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are ruled of prudencie, which (as Cicero telleth in his particions ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toriall) in her proper affayres is accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed to be termed domeſticall, and in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon caſes politike, we ſhal deſcriue.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>Of Domesticall gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernance. Cap. xiij.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ee haue ſpoken of that part of wiſdom which is tried in the operacions of euery man: Now we muſte intreate of that which is comprehended in the houſhoulde duties whome the Greekes tearme <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that is to wit, conſideracion well to trade the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ily, either which is touchinge the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruacion of houſewifery affaire. This
<pb facs="tcp:19634:33"/> reſpect is buſied verely in the houſhold, as in the mattier which it handleth: to whom that ſcope is propounded, that it be wittelye gouerned for the worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of euery parſon. Euery Family conſiſteth of two partes, the man, and the ſubſtaunce. The man compriſeth the Huſband, or the Maiſter, the wife, the Children, the ſeruauntes: But the ſubſtaunce conteyneth the houſe and worldly pealthe. Let vs briefly reaſon of theſe orderly, and let vs take begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the dutie of the good man of the houſe, becauſe he is the firſt Original of a Family to be ordained. The Lorde of the place then, whom we vnderſtande by nature ſtudious of freendſhip and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finity, &amp; getting children, ought both to know, and be able to protecte the ſoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etie of his wife and Children, and gent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and curteouſly to rule ouer his, both Children and Seruauntes: of which they oftentimes are of a more honeſt nature, theſe commonly of a more vile. The family now conſtituted, nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is to be ſought for, ſuſtenance, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parell and harborough whiche may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fende
<pb facs="tcp:19634:33"/> vs from ſtormes, and inrodes of Beaſtes. Groundtilthe, Huntinge, Hawking, Fiſhinge, labour ſhall mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Foode. Now whereas the goodman and wife are the cheefeſt and effeciente cauſes of Houſhould, and the Children, and Seruauntes, as it weare certaine Inſtrumentes, and euerie one are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaunt in the houſe and ſubſtaunce as the mattier: we in this place firſt &amp; for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt will vtter a few wordes of them: and then wee ſhall expreſſe the Offices of the perſons a little before nomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. Before all others a manſion place is to be ſought for, which the neceſſitie of life compelled men to Builde, that they might haue whether to trudge, as birdes into their Neſtes, Beaſtes, into their couerts: In the beginning houſes were erected for a ſeruiceable vſe, forth with by littel and littel Ornamentes approched therto. Eſpecially a confide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racion is to bee had of the profite and commodity, and next of eche ones dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie. Ouermuche coſte and hurtfull ſumptuouſnes, it not to be admitted in building, and that the houſe, as he coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeled,
<pb facs="tcp:19634:34"/> want not ground. The holeſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and fitneſſe of place is to be view<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and manie moe, which Victrunius and Philoſophers, who haue written, <hi>de re familiari,</hi> diligently haue expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. And hetherto recheth the diſcourſe of the houſe: henceforth wee ought to diſpute of affaires apperteining to Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milie. That is either naturall, and the worthieſte, of all: as Huſbandry, Hunting, Fiſhing, Or els artificious, which conſidereth gaine: as traueiles &amp; trades throughe which the liuinge is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>depted. Beſides there are others part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly liberall, partely ſeruile, as the crafte of Painting, as the drawinge of ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes, as the ſcience of buildinge, which are brought to perfection both by witte and trauaile. Of theſe Artes (which are many and chaungeable, inuented for the diuers wantes of men) the good man of the houſe ought to put that in practiſe in whiche he ſhall haue ſkill, and ſhould prouide ſuſtenaunce honeſtly for him and his without pillinge and pollinge of any man: He ought to auoyde incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modious and hatefull trades, and ought
<pb facs="tcp:19634:34"/> to ſearche for the profitable. The lucre of Vſurers, and of Eſcheters, or of ſuch as do ſelfe any maner of thing for a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faiture is odious. Likewiſe the gaine of thoſe Marchauntes who are enriched with forged tales is filthy, which be the ſeruauntes of Delyces. The maiſter of the houſe ought to preſerue ſuch things which are gotten, &amp; ought to vſe them temperatly, and ought to vnderſtande that it is not leſſer cunninge to ſaue them than to procure them. And theſe thinges haue wee compendiouſly made manifeſt touchinge the houſe and houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde prouiſion: Now we will purſue the charges or offices of houſhold dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, and firſt of the good man, of whom before we began to treate of. His chee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſte regarde ſhalbee, to marry a wife, which is a companion and a copartner of life and goods, honeſt, prudent, welny as riche as him ſelfe, not proude, nor more curious then néedeth, or els way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde, whiche may bothe be loued, and loue. He ſhal intreate her no otherwiſe than him ſelfe a Leagfellow and a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tener as of Seruice and Domeſticall
<pb facs="tcp:19634:35"/> toyle, ſo likewiſe of all caſualties and affaires: And perdie he ſhall loue her only ioigned vnto him with a bonde not able to be diſſolued, and as becommeth a free woman, he ſhall not withhold her ouer rigorouſly, if ſo that no iuſte feare of Chaſtity doth interrupte. Neither ſhall he handle her vnciuily, but honeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, godly, comely, courteouſly, gentelly, that he remember how he is a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an man, the head perdie of his wife, but whome he oughte to tender as the halfe part of him ſelfe, and permit her alſo to vſe her certaine peculier right. He ſhall traine vp the Children begotten of his wife diligently, he ſhall faſhion them to vertue and godlineſſe beyng as yet ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and ſhal prouide them to be inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with holſome and expedient trades: he ſhal ſeeke his pelth by his owne tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell and induſtrie vertuouſly, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out enuie: and he ſhal keepe a commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable trade of clodding ſubſtance, either by makyng of Contractes, either by do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng of workes, or els through more ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt and better meanes to eſpie out ri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ches and promocions (whiche are ver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19634:35"/> many) he ſhall miniſter foode bothe to himſelf and his, if neceſſitie ſhall vrge him to ſeeke. If ſo be the wealth is not to be gotten with paynes takynge, but is left of the parentes, he ſhal protecte the ſame hedely, &amp; he ſhal imploy coſtes wiſely and moderatly, an aduyſe beyng had of the place and condition, that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he may be accompted a greedy gut, nor an outragious ſpender, and had leif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer at al ſeaſon both to be recitened, and alſo to be more liberal, than couetous. If the maſter hath ſeruauntes, he ſhall know to vſe them wel, and he ſhal in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct them, and ſhal freendly intreate them. But if they being hyred for meed do faithfully ſerue, he ſhal conſider their paynes, and ſhal exerciſe them in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t trauel, he ſhal not fatigate them: and he ſhal nouriſh them as it becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, he ſhal ſee vnto them as the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie inſtrumentes of the houſe, and he ſhal keepe them in awe, nor ſhal per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit them to be aduaunced arrogantly. He ſhal pay them gentely their coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant at due time. If there ſhalbe many ſeruantes, they are to be preferre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:19634:36"/> to a more excellent or vyler office as ech ones capacitie requireth. The wyfe ought to reſpecte the houſe paine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and dayly, and ought to be preſent at domeſticall doynges, ſhe ought to marke the chayres of her ſeruantes: ſhe ought to reuerence her huſbande, not curſt and ſnappiſh, but pudique, and ſhe ought to keepe cleanly both her maydes and children, and al the reſt pliant and peaſible in their office: She ought not to be ſtately, not ſumptuous, nor yet beaſtly, but appareled with decent at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier accordyng to habilitie. Her chiefeſt regard ought to be in bringyng vp her children honeſtly. She ought to deuyſe to encreaſe her goods, &amp; ought to keepe that with ſoberneſſe, whiche is gotten with the toyle of her huſband. The chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren ought to reuerence their parentes they ought to loue them &amp; (as God him ſelfe hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded) they ought to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour them, they ought willingly to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundements, they ought to be obedient to them in all reſpectes, they ought likewiſe to obey their ſchole maſters, which are the inſtructours of
<pb facs="tcp:19634:36"/> the minde, &amp; as it were ſecond parents, For they both are charged w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> one thing, to trayne vp youthe vertuouſly. They ought to apply the ſtudies appoynted them, they ſhould eſchew idleneſſe and pleaſure before the reſt as pernicious plagues: they ought to reuerence their elders, and magiſtrates as well ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall as temporall, and the honeſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and diſcreete: But they ought to eſteeme thoſe with a certayne princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal good will of whom both their vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce and harte are decked with right excellent ſciences vnto all humanitie. The ſeruantes ought to be obedient and faithfull to their mayſters, herke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng to their precept, and alwaies bent to finiſh their commaundement: they ought to haue in reuerence, &amp; loue their maiſters as their parentes; they ought to be thriftie, appayde with a moderate liuing, and requiſite apparel, thei ought willyngly to enlarge the riches of their mayſters, they ought to ſteale nothyng priuily: They ought paciently to ſuffer their mayſter, if he ſhalbe more curious than needeth; if he ſhalbe more eaſie to
<pb facs="tcp:19634:37"/> pleaſe, they may not neglecte him.</p>
               <p>Whether it be leiful for Chriſtians, to haue bondemen, and whether any may be bondmen by nature (which thing A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtotle alloweth) I leaue to be diſcuſſed of others.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>Of Politike gouernance. Cap. xiiij.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Ven as a Family conſiſteth of particuler men, ſo doth a City of many Families, of which preſently we will debate. In a common weale wel to be gouerned, Prudencie is cheefely tried, withoute which no ſocietie of man can be ruled. Politike gouernaunce, or els a weale Publike is defined of Plutarchus in his booke <hi>De tribus Reipub. generibus,</hi> a ſtate and order of a Citie, to be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in ruling of matters. This Ciuill wiſdom preſcribeth the actions of Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens: eke is altogether occupied in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendinge the ſocietie of man, as in the
<pb facs="tcp:19634:37"/> matter which it hath taken in hand to be reaſoned vpon: and hath that ſcope propounded vnto her ſelfe, that the weale publik may be diſcretly handled, and that prouiſion may be made for the ſauegard of the inhabitantes. Ariſtotle gaue this difference betwixt a Family and a common wealth, that in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealthe there ſhoulde be an equa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of prerogatiue, by which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> higheſt ſhoulde be valued with the lowe: But in the houſhold the Maiſter ſhould haue the Empire of a King ouer his children and Seruauntes, as his Subiectes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge whom the like equality can not be. Of common weales ſixe fourmes are recited: three good, which the prince, the Nobilitie and the commens do mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter iuſtfully, and conueniently for for the general profite of the whole Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: and ſo many wicked, which the Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunte, and the bande of a fewe, and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eane people do gouern as their owne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt impelleth them, haling all thinges <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o their proper behoofe. There appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eth no Citie of any nation, which may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ot be referred to ſome of theſe. That
<pb facs="tcp:19634:38" rendition="simple:additions"/> Common weale whiche conſiſteth of them three whiche are eſteemed good, Cicero in his bookes <hi>De Repub:</hi> ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth to be beſt, by reaſon it is more excelent, more profitable, and of lenger perpetuitie than the reſt. Amonge the Romanes, after the kynges expelled out of their Realmes, euen vnto Iulius and <hi>Auguſtus Reſpub: Democratica,</hi> the fourme of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon wealth where the people had authoritie without any other ſtate ſeemeth to haue ben ſo tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pred with a certaine moderation of the kyngdome of <hi>Ariſtocratia</hi> whiche is a ſtate of a Weale publike, where many rule that are moſte worthie in vertue, and proweſſe, that a certaine Princely maieſtie did excell in the Conſuls <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtocraria</hi> in the ſenators, <hi>Democratia</hi> in the Tribunes of the common ſorte, but the cheefeſt power was in the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of the people. Now a princely Monarchy ratified by the aduice of pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dente Peeres, and Sauced with vnre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moouable decrées appeareth worthelie to be aduaunced before al others for co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity
<pb facs="tcp:19634:38" rendition="simple:additions"/> and quietneſſe eſpecialy ſithens not by election, but throughe a certaine Heauenlie prouidence Realmes are tranſported to the Children of Kinges &amp; Princes generated through the Lawe of bloud beinge the ſucceſſours of their Parents, or vnto the next of aliaunce. Becauſe perdy a Citie conſiſteth of the multitude of Cittizens leadinge their liues vprightly, let vs manifeſt what ones they ought to be. He is to be na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med a good Citizen of his countrie, who being trimmed with ciuill vertues, and eſpicially with Iuſtice and Fortitude, whom Prudence, and Temperaunce, do moderate, may be able to perfourme very well not only Domeſtical and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milier offices, but alſo Publike both at home, and in warre. There is neede of common Schoolemaiſters bothe honeſt and lerned to declare vertues, through whoſe trauel Children gaily inſtituted from their youth, may depart exquiſite in honeſty and Godlineſſe, and through the knowledge of moſt excellent mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, become profitable members to their countrie. If ſo be the riches of the
<pb facs="tcp:19634:39"/> Parentes may not beare, that their Children by leaſure may be enriched with liberall ſtudies: the next remedie is that they be learned ſom kinde of oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupacion, whereby they may get their liuing. Ydleneſſe and pleaſure vere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly are diligently to be ſhunned of all men: Alwaies ſtudie, and an honeſte and commodious exerciſe bothe of the minde and body is to be required. By al meanes poſſible it is to be laboured of all good citizens, but principally of the Parents and inſtructours, that by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon children, and youthſtate can eaſilie imitate any thinge, they may lighten them in the purity of life, and may be a paterne of vertu to their younger: Let euery occaſion of treſpaſſyng, as much as habilitie will geue leaue, be taken away: Let the enticementes of concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcence and wantonneſſe be remoued: Let obedience be exhibited to the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, if he be good. As to the father of the country, vnto whom authoritie is geuen from aboue: But if he be ill, let him pacienly be ſuffered, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſedicion modeſtly and meekely be
<pb facs="tcp:19634:39"/> admoniſhed of his duty. Let the Lawes be obſerued: Let Religion cheefely be reuerenced: Let peace and concord be kept among the Citizens. Let euery cauſe of diſcord be eſchewed. Let euery manne haue a reſpect to his owne buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: Neither let any man giue him ſelfe to beare Office in the common weale vnleſſe he be called: Let reſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies be ſoughte for: Let pencions be paide: Let the countrey be moſt deare to euery man, for whom a good Citezen ſhall not feare to die, if neede ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire. For the cheefeſt loue next vnto God is due to the Countrey, and to the Magiſtrate: the next to the Parentes and kinſfulke, the third to the Citizens linked or vnited together through the commonneſſe of Lawe. Let Foriners or Straungers peruſe their buſineſſe, nor let them be ouer inqiſitiue in other mens affaires. Let them behaue them elues modeſtly. It is the charge of a magiſtrate, to gouerne the weale pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like wittily: to vſe them moderately and warily, ouer whom he beareth rule (whiche he cannot abſolue, vnleſſe he
<pb facs="tcp:19634:40"/> be of an honeſt minde and good iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as a wyſe and prudent man) to mainteyne the lawes, that they may be obſerued, to the whiche alſo he himſelfe ſhall obey: To behaue himſelf decently accordyng to the dignitie of ſtate, which he hath put on, courteouſly, modeſtly, iuſtly, not filthely, not couetouſly, not proudely, not waiwardly, not cruelly: to geue vpright ſentence to al men: to mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter no rigorouſneſſe or parcialitie: to extende clemencie, ſharpeneſſe, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie in caſtigations and puniſhments: leſſe he ſhuld chaſtice ſome more ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, others more ſoftly which are accuſed of one matter, except any thyng inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt, that may inforce him ſo to worke agaynſt his will: After one faſhion to care for all the Citezens both riche and poore, noble and baſe: to thinke himſelf to be the father of the common wealth: to purney thinges behoueable for the Citie, as Corne, if by chaunce ſcarcitie and dearth of grayne ſhould be feared, as other thynges of whiche there ſhalbe néede in the extremities of the common wealth: And then next to haue an eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall
<pb facs="tcp:19634:40"/> regarde of the poore, when as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie greatly oppreſſeth, chiefly a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon penury, what? one is the pouertie of corne. It ſhall be his parte to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne ſtraungers, and alians, and pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimes freendly and fauorably, leſſe the citie ſhould be il ſpoken of among foren Nations: To conclude, it lieth in him to referre all his cogitations to the ſaue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the common wealth: to attende vpon her profits and vtilities, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to cheriſh euery where the dignitie and reputation thereof. And becauſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne cannot ſuſtaine all the dueties, it is expedient that diuers magiſtrates vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake diuers offices: of which al not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding there ought to be the like ſtudie, to tender the profits of the cite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens, and more earneſtly to ſeeke for the commoditie and ſafegard of them, than their owne. If ſo fortune ſerue that battell is to be waged (whereas nothynge more pernicious than it can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e inſpired of God into the common <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ealth.) Let that of Terence be borne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>way. <hi>Conſilio omnia prius experiri, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uain armis, ſaprentem decet.</hi> It be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth
<pb facs="tcp:19634:41"/> a wyſe man firſt to aſſault all thinges with aduiſe, than with dent of ſworde. If the daunger cannot be with holden which is threatned all men, wee muſt geue the onſet prudently, and we muſt repell it valiauntly, yet no battel is to be enterpriſed but that whiche is iuſt: to execute the which wel, an ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>eſt preparacion is to be taken in hand: ſtoute Champions are to be ſought for and ſkilful of Marcial feates, nor ſtrong men only, but alſo witty and Politike: Souldiars muſt be ſought out ſpeedely, and a choiſe is to be gathered of them: Argent is to be Coyned, which truly is termed <hi>Nemus belli</hi> the ſinew of war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare: The Souldiars are to be kept in office, vnto whom (that he may appeare to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ear the maiſtry) wage is to be attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted at due time: And chary heede is to be had that they ſpoyle not them whom they are hyred to protect: which is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently and more than inough expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimented by the olde complaynt, bothe of countrie men and Citizens, what a cruell and lothſome a thynge it is to the miſerable comminaltie. It is not meete
<pb facs="tcp:19634:41"/> that a Magiſtrate be altogether rude and vnſkilful of chiualry. And although at theſe daies there is a far contrary fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of waging Battel than in auncient times, by reaſon of the new inuencion of Helliſh fire, yet the booke of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial policy ſhal auaile very greatly, as of <hi>Flanius vegetius, Iulius Frontinus, Ali<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> and ſuch like, throughe peruſing of which a greate knowledge of warfare ſhal be procured: the which is to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by the experience of olde and ſturdy Souldiars which haue been pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent at ſundry Skirmiſhes, and of ſtout and Prudente Capitaines which haue learned warlike proweſſe through long practiſe: who would doubte it to becom moſte abſolute? Neither doth this ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence appeare leſſe conducible to the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, than Sage wiſdome, or whatſoeuer crafte there is commodious for life.</p>
               <p>For wheras ther be three ſortes of men in the common wealthe: as officers, which ſhould rule wel and iuſtly: as Capitaines &amp; Souldioures which ſhould faithfully and valiauntly defend: as ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificers bothe of comlie and vndecente
<pb facs="tcp:19634:42"/> diſciplines, which ſhould aide the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary and profitable trades: Yet vnto al them ought there to be a like indeuoure to maintaine the weale Publike with amiable agreement. And thus muche in Politike Prudence to be conſidered.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>Of Vices contrary to vviſdom. Cap. xv.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Gnoraunce is a vice co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to wiſdom, who likewiſe after a contrary ſort may be defined: An vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſkilfulneſſe to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne good and euill thinges, or els to out finde the truth, or to determine what is to be doone, or what is to be left of. This is a common plague to all vices, as prudencie to ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, becauſe no vertue can want the aduiſe of wiſdom: and euery vniuſt, and ſluggiſh and vntemperate perſon, the ſame ought to be called vnwiſe. The companions of imprudence be, the er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour
<pb facs="tcp:19634:42"/> of the mynde, and temeritie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant to perfect iudgement: and the foolyſh perſon attributeth much vnto Fortune, whom he reuerenceth as a Goddeſſe where as he vſeth not reaſon and counſell: and yelding his good will to affections doeth commonly admit thoſe thynges, of which afterwardes he repenteth: or els co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarywiſe through cowardlyneſſe and negligence neither regardeth his children nor wife, and ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth no inſtruction in his houſeholde, and no kinde of authoritie. If ſuche a Magiſtrate ſhalbe in the weale publike the wicked will ſuppoſe that a licence is miniſtred vnto them to treade a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe: if there be ſuche a Capitayne the Souldiours will become daſtardes, yea and they whom he reteyned valiaunt, what manner of felowes <hi>Scipio Ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lianus</hi> founde before the deſtruction of <hi>Numantia,</hi> whom he reduced to theyr antique manlineſſe Marciall diſcipline reſtored, and ouerſlipped no occaſion of any worthy feate to be practiſed.</p>
               <p>Wilineſſe verely is a vice, whiche with a certaine cloke of vertu deludeth
<pb facs="tcp:19634:43"/> the vncircumſpect: which ſith it purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth not to trauell for the truthe, it can not be called wiſdom, but a ſuttell and a Foxlike counterfaiter of Prudencie: who yet ſomewhiles is compted a ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, if it be wreſted vnto a commodious ende. But the partes and operations of Prudence beyng perceiued, it ſhall not be a perplexed buſineſſe to vndermine the contrarie: Notwithſtandynge wee muſt be very wary that vices do not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue vs, whiche appeare to counterfet vertue. Doubtleſſe vertue her ſelfe is a mediocritie welnie betwixt two extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, but of whiche thone is a manifeſt dice, and is apertly perceiued: as when ignorance is ſet againſt wiſdom, wrong againſt Iuſtice, cowardneſſe agaynſt Fortitude, Intemperance, agaynſt Temperaunce, Couetouſneſſe, againſt Liberalitie. But the other becauſe he is a vice, couſin germain to Vertue is not ſo eaſely eſpied, as when craftineſſe or ſubtiltie is gaiged agaynſt wiſedome, cruelty againſt Iuſtice, lewdhardineſſe agaynſt manlineſſe, an outragiouſneſſe in deſpiſing of pleaſures agaynſt tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance,
<pb facs="tcp:19634:43"/> Prodigalitie againſt liberali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, Obſtinacy agaynſt perſeuerance. For as Ouide ſaies.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>And miſchiefes are of kinne to good,</l>
                  <l>for vnder that deceiptfull weede,</l>
                  <l>Vertue oftetimes hath borne the checke,</l>
                  <l>for vices rootes who bringe the ſeede.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <head>Of Iuſtice. Cap. xvi.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Icero calleth Iuſtice <hi>Dominam ommum &amp; reginam virtutum,</hi> The Lady and Princeſſe of al vertues: and defines it, a perfection of the minde, whiche the common vtilitie beyng maintened, yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to euery one his ſtatelineſſe: and he calleth it, an affection of the minde, whiche geueth to eche one his due, and defendeth the ſocietie of humain felow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip bountifully and egally. Moreouer it is diſcribed of the ſame author: An eueneſſe, geuynge euery one his right accordyng to the dignitie and deſert of euery perſon: Ariſtotle calleth it, an
<pb facs="tcp:19634:44"/> affection of the minde, wherby men are fit to worke iuſtfully, and by whiche both they will and do ſuch thinges as be rightful: &amp; after the ſame ſorte we may manifeſt iniuſtice, by which men exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe wronge, and are voluntarily infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to vnlawfull matters. The La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiers terme it, a conſtant and a perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall will miniſtryng to euery man his right. For Iuſtice is conuerſant in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtribution of equitie, as in the mattier, that the equalitie, whiche the law doth procreate, may be preſerued. There be vices repugnant to euery one, to this iniuſtice, to the other iniurie: To For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude and Temperance more. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is more expedient than this vertu to mainteyne the ſocietie of humaine kinde, nothing more agreable to nature who hath faſhioned vs vnto al humanity and natural beneuolence. If ſo be wee are borne for this felowſhip (as mini-only Cicero confirmeth in his firſt bake <hi>De legibus</hi>) we muſt confeſſe that we in like caſe are ingendred for Iuſtice with out whiche that ſocietie and felowſhip cannot conſiſte: and that the ſame is
<pb facs="tcp:19634:44"/> naturally engraffed in vs as a Torche caried before one to work rightful mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, &amp; to eſchew the contrarie, through the opinion of vndeceiuable reaſon, ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen by the conſent and benefit of God: whiche if it be ratified with the vſe of operation, then at length a cuſtome &amp; a perfection of vertue ſhalbe procured, wherof Nature hath geuen as it were litle ſparkes. Touchyng that which is called in queſtion concerning the medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ocritie of Iuſtice, ſhe is verely (as Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotle deemeth) a meane: but ſhe is pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced betwixt both extremities after ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſorte than y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſidue of the vertues Morall, who is referred vnto right and euenneſſe: in preſeruacion of which ſhe is conuerſante, euen as iniuſtice and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurie the diſquieter of egall dealing and rightfulneſſe is buſied in vnequalitie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <head>Of the partes of Iuſtice. Cap. xvij.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:19634:45"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE partes of Iuſtice be two: the one common and vniuerſall, which is occupied in preſeruacion of the right of humane ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cietie, and it conſidereth a common good, and learneth vs to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence right and equity: the other pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate, which is verified in reſtoring to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery man what is duetiful. And this is double: One which reteineth equali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in fourmes of choppinge and chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging together, and in affaires, which v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually is called <hi>Commutatiua:</hi> Another which is occupied in diſtribution of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noures accordinge to ech mans worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, which they tearme <hi>Diſtributiuam.</hi> The charge of common Iuſtice is to maintaine law, and equitie, whervpon he is called a iuſt manne, who ſheweth him ſelfe obedient to all cuſtoms. Law is defined of Cicero, a reaſon engraffed of nature, whiche commaundeth thoſe thinges which are to be taken in hand, and forbiddeth the contrary: And in like ſorte, a right reaſon, and deriued from the mighte of the Gods, charging
<pb facs="tcp:19634:45"/> ſuch matters as are honeſt, diſanulling the contrary. Hether all decrées may be referred, ſtatutes, manners, ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunces, expedient for the ſauegarde of the weale publike in obſeruing of which Iuſtice is tried, in violating of which iniuſtice. Equitie coupleth her ſelfe to the law, who folowinge the righte ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of reaſon, doth gouerne the lawe written, and as the worthieſt interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toure of al lawes, doth wittily aſſwage rigorous ſharpeneſſe according to the place, oportunity, and diſpoſitions of men. That member of priuate Iuſtice which is Tituled, <hi>Diſtributiua,</hi> pertea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth cheefly vnto magiſtrates: who not only is occupied in grauntinge Offices and rewardes, but alſo in appointinge puniſhments, that with an equal lawe the citizens may be ruled, both the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous beneficed, and the naughty cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected. This perdie is the charge of a Magiſtrate: but the intelligence of this vertue is neceſſarie for all men, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery man may vnderſtande his place whiche he ſhould keepe in the common wealth, and the dutie whiche he ſhould
<pb facs="tcp:19634:46"/> execute: and ſhould attribute and leaue vnto euery one bothe place and dutie, and ſhould knowe him ſelfe, nor ſhould glory ouer much in his proper conceite. This vertue by reaſon eſpecially it ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dieth to ſuccour equality, is compared to Geometricall proporcion, in which a like conſideration is had of greater and leſſer numbers. But that parcel which they terme <hi>Commutatiuam</hi> is occupied in bargaininges of men, and teacheth to yéelde vnto euery man his owne, that ware for ware, the value for the chaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer be geeuen, perfecte equality beinge kepte: and this hath a care rather to render home debte, than to diſtribute promocion to the worthier: Wherfore in like caſe it is clogged with Arithme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall proporcion, becauſe in this the numbers, in the other an indifferency of reaſon is reſpected. This is conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaunt in contractes which the Lawyers do diſplay: the other in Dignities and penalties, which are appointed of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates. And hetherto of al kinde of Iuſtice, and her partes. But becauſe vnto theſe other ſixe members are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uected
<pb facs="tcp:19634:46"/> defined of Cicero in his bookes <hi>De Inuentione:</hi> Religion, Pietie, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence, Trouth, Reuenging, Thank: to whiche ſhalbe adioyned liberalitie, magnificence, frendſhip, and vices diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gréeable to euery one: of theſe alſo we muſt expreſſe our opinion. Theſe ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues by reaſon, they conſiſt through the equality of reaſon, they ſeeme to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected vnto diſtributing Iuſtice, like as euerye varitye of bargaines to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaunging.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <head>Of the ſix partes of Iustice conſtituted of Cicero, and their vices, and of ſom other vvhich be vvelnie of the ſame nature. Cap. xviij.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Icero in his ſecond booke <hi>De Inuentione</hi> hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſed thrée partes of Iuſtice: the law natural, vſual, and the law leiful.
<pb facs="tcp:19634:47"/> And the law natural he defineth, which opinion may not bring to vs, but a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine inſtruction naturall, wherof he nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>breth ſix members, which euen now I haue declared. Religion is one, a right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe towardes God, either a piety wherby we adore him: ſo called as Lac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tantius writeth in his fourth booke. <hi>A religando,</hi> of ſure binding, by reaſon for this cauſe we are engendred, that we may exhibite iuſt and dutifull ſeruyces vnto God begetting vs, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhuld him onely acknowledge, that him we ſhould folow. We are linked and faſtned vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God with this bonde of godlineſſe. Plutarchus doth interpreate Religion, <hi>Scientiam rerum Dominarum,</hi> a ſcience of diuine matters: wee terme it <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutem</hi> a Vertue, by which a iuſte and a trewe worſhip is geuen to God. The which (as of all vertues) ſo likewiſe we ſhal wel cal it the ground, and doubtles the Parente and Mother of Iuſtice. Nothinge is more neceſſary than this vertue to preſerue the common wealth and to lead the life egally, and without couine amonge the Citizens: ſithe no
<pb facs="tcp:19634:47"/> ſtrength may rather banniſh men from all vnthriftineſſe, than if they ſhal per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue that theare is affliction prepared of God for the tranſgreſſoures, and a path made open vnto Heauen and vnto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ternal felicity for ſuche as leade their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ues godly and iuſtly. There hath been <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>et neuer any Nation ſo Barbarous which hath not fauoured ſom Religion although it were falſe, and forbidden from working of iniury through y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> feare of ſom God, wheras an Othe was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compted a moſt ſtreight band to wring their faith together. What is it expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diente that Chriſtians do? to whome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aithfulneſſe is geuen the grounde of al <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eligion of Ieſus Chriſt our Lorde and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>auiour, and the holy Apoſtles and his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ucceſſours, ſo ratified that neither by any humayne force, nor yet infernall rage it may be ouerthrowen: I ſay, what is it meete for them to doo, vnto whom leading their liues with vertue God himſelfe hath propoſed a ſure hope of bliſful and ſempiternal life: through the confidence of whoſe promiſe, what true godly man for ſanctified religion
<pb facs="tcp:19634:48"/> will ſtagger to leſe his breathe, if neede ſhall require? How eaſely might all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurie be put to flight if that precept of God our ſauiour &amp; maiſter were deeply grauen in all mens mindes. <hi>Quod tibi fieri nolis, alteri nefeceris,</hi> What thou wilt not to be committed agaynſt thy ſelfe, thou ſhalt not do to another. Which ſentence wiſe felowes alſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting from our religion haue ſo mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueiled at, that they eſteemed nothynge more diuine, that nothing coulde be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered more auayleable to maynteyne the fellowſhip of men. Contrarious to Religion is ſuperſticion, a ſcrupuloſitie of holineſſe, which honoureth the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly power not as it ought, either a vaine and a fooliſh honour of God: than which vice impietie towardes God and the contempte of reuerente dreade is ſurely a more deteſtable miſchiefe: by which all faith is turned vpſide downe, by which periury, by which Sacrilegies are eſtabliſhed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:19634:48"/>
               <head>Of Godlyneſſe. Cap. xix.</head>
               <p>IN the ſeconde place Pietie is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herſed of Cicero, which although it be defined ſome whiles of him, a Iuſtice towardes the Goddes that it ſhould be the ſame whiche Religion is: yet moſt commonly it is taken for Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice towardes our progenitours, or els for a thankefull good wil towardes our Parentes. But in his bookes of Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torike, Pietie is more abſolutely defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed, through which duetie, and an ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt reuerence is geuen vnto Aliaunce, and to them which are well willinge to theyr countrey. And in like ſort in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other place. Pietie is, which geueth in charge to obſerue duetie towardes our countrie, our parents and others our kynſefolke. This laſte vertue is well coupled to Religion, becauſe the cheifeſt worſhip is to be geuen to God, the next to the Parentes, and next of kinne, and eſpecially to the countrey, whiche one, Cicero ſaieth comprehendeth all chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. Impiety is a contrary vice to God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:19634:49"/> towards ſuch to whom beneuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence and loue is due. Againſt this ſo deteſtable a wickedneſſe, when as yet the title of murder was vnknowen, it was not neceſſary to eſtabliſh a lawe: but afterwards when they began, who violatyng the law of nature, and more brutiſh than brute beaſts, did murther &amp; deſpoyle them of whom they had recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued life, a moſt rigorous law was rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, of which declaration is made in the digeſtes vnder the title, <hi>Ad L. Pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peiam, de patricidus.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="chapter">
               <head>Of Reuerence. Cap. xx.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Euerence is, by which we honoure and worſhip the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> who excel vs in age, either in wiſdome, either in dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, or in any eſtimacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For that God him ſelfe geueth in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundment by the law of nature, that with due obeyſaunce and honoure we ſhould reuerence our parentes and the Magiſtrates whom he woulde to rule
<pb facs="tcp:19634:49"/> ouer vs. This vertue of obedience is ſo neceſſary, that withoute it neither a houſe, neither a Citie, nor any fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip can remaine. How pernicious the vice repugnaunte to obedience is, the gréeuous ruine of the firſt parentes of al mankind, which hath tormented eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry mothers Sonne, hath geuen a leſſon to vs. This enormitye ſpringeth of Pride, and arrogancye and of <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> through which any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by ouerweening in him ſelfe to well, and fauouringe his perſon, maketh him ſelf another couſin to God almighty. Nothinge verely is more odious than pride both to God and men. For at all ſeaſons, as the Latin Tragical writer recordeth, <hi>Sequitur ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perbos vltor a tergo Deus,</hi> God that ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth vengeaunce foloweth the lofty be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde their backes. The fal of wicked Angels whiche cannot be repaired, and than the which none hath bin more gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous at any time doth witnes the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:19634:50"/>
               <head>Of Trouth. Cap. xxi.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Routh is (ſaieth Cicero) throughe whiche thoſe thinges are ſayde to be vnchaunged whiche are, or haue been, or els are aboute to come: Either a right perfection of the minde wherby any man both telleth the truthe, either in affyrmyng, or els in deniyng, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo pretendeth no ſubteltie: whereof he may be called a true ſpeaker. It is a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie vertue to make bargaynes, in whom faith ought to beare rule, which is defined, a conſtancie and a ſoothe of ſayinges and doynges: neither is truth any other thinge in contractes and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comptes, than faith: whiche if it be dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently obſerued, the proper office of duetie ſhalbe fulfilled: which is to yelde vnto euery man his owne. A lie is a vice contrarie to veritie, &amp; in like ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner the malicious inuencions of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſmes, and all deceipte and diſſimula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion and counterfaityng, and alſo arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancie.
<pb facs="tcp:19634:50"/> A forged deuiſe is miſcheuous and pernicious vnto the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon wealth for it wreſteth a man from God which is true, and the welſpryng of al verity, and purchaſeth him freendſhip with the Deuill, and bringeth euerlaſtyng death to the ſoule: and violateth humaine ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cietie with a falſe Merchaundiſe, and incenſeth hatreds and diſcordes through a leaſyng tongue. That boſtinge, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially fooliſh of ſome that are too glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in their owne eſtate, is irkeſome to the learned. Certes an alteration to be abandoned. Clokyng alſo is vnſeemely for an honeſt man, who ſpeaketh no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe then he thinketh: he doth not commend him in preſence, whom he diſprayſeth in abſence: he counterfai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth and worketh wilily not with male ingine, but wittily, if neede ſhoulde en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="chapter">
               <head>Of Reuengement. Cap. xxij.</head>
               <p>REuengement is (ſaith Cicero) by whiche violence, and iniurie, and
<pb facs="tcp:19634:51"/> whatſoeuer at any time is like to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodite, may be repelled by defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding or auengyng. And it is defined a taking of puniſhment, by which we put of from vs a diſpight either by ſhunning hit, or by repaying the like. But this latter definition for this cauſe appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to vs littel commodious, becauſe it conteineth priuate reuengement, like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe alowed of him in his firſt booke of Deuties: whiche wee know to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued not only of Chriſtians, but alſo of prophane Philoſophers, and ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of our Religion, who imitatynge the rule of nature did iudge it better to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, than to commit iniurie: becauſe that may be done iuſtly, and this can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be accompliſhed without iniuſtice, as Ariſtotle alſo learneth in his .v. booke of Ethikes. That likewiſe may be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed to pacience, doubtleſſe an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent vertue: this perdie to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie vice. Neither truly ought any man to thinke that any other talke is miniſtred, than that he may repel force by force, if it may not be eſchewed: and that for to defend, not to damage or els
<pb facs="tcp:19634:51"/> to reuenge: for a minde to diſcommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite breaketh iuſtice the leiful reuenge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is committed of God vnto the Magiſtrates, which be the miniſters of lawes: but withholden from priuate perſons, vnto whom no title of puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhinge is attributed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="chapter">
               <head>Of Thanke. Cap. xxiij.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hanke whiche vſually is called gratitudo, kinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, is (ſaieth Cicero) in whiche the memorie of the frendſhippes and frendly tournes of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther man, and a good will to repay an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other is comprehended. The ſame man telleth: Thanke is which ought to vſe obſeruaunce in the remembrance and recompence of duties, and honours, and frendſhips. It is more compendiouſly deſcriued, A faithful memory of a thank<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full minde, Or els a deſier mindefull to doo one good turne and pleaſure for another: and perhaps it is defined more
<pb facs="tcp:19634:52"/> fitly: by reaſon this vertue is conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant in receauynge, rather than in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge. For to geue, is a pointe of libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralitie: To receyue with a good will, and to be willinge to repay, is the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertie of thanke. It is his parte to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get the benefit beſtowed, nor to wayte for a recompence. And to this man it belongeth to remember hit, and wher oportunitie geueth occaſion with an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerplus alſo, if he may, and he ought to thinke the reward wel to be placed, and to be willyng to render the ſame redily and yet to retayne a perpetual reporte of the pleaſure exhibited. On bothe the partes héede is to be taken that the thing which either is geuen, or reſtored be profitable and commodious for him to whom it is geuen or reſtored, and iuſt fully gotten, leſſe we ſhould be libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral and grateful on another ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s purſe.</p>
               <p>The vice repugnant to kindeneſſe is commonly termed ingratitude: which may be defined, a forgetfulneſſe of a good turne receyued: and either an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willyng thanke, or none, or els (whiche is worſt of all) a diſpleaſure requited:
<pb facs="tcp:19634:52"/> whiche is the cheefeſt iniuſtice, than whiche nothyng can be more hateful to all men.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="chapter">
               <head>Of Compaſsion. Cap. xxiiij.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ompaſſion, a moſte ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable vertue to God, is thought good aptely to be annected vnto theſe. For as we do owe Loue, truth and faith to al men godlineſſe to few, reuengement to ſuch as do wrong, kindeneſſe to them as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue wel, ſo are we bounde to ſhewe mercie vnto them which ſuffer afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. I cal not compaſſion verily in this place. <hi>Agritudinem</hi> a heauineſſe, or els as Seneca, a vice of the mindes ouer muche fauouringe wretchedneſſe, but a vertue through which the mind is pric<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked with the miſeries and calamities of another man to ſuccour the oppreſſed.</p>
               <p>Compaſſion is defined of Cicero, a greef through anothers aduerſity: Of Sene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca in his bookes <hi>De Clemencia,</hi> a ſmart
<pb facs="tcp:19634:53"/> of the minde, or els a ſorowfulneſſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eyued by other mens harmes, whiche <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e déemeth to chance to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vndeſeruing. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut he indeuoreth to prooue that this is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vice in theſe wordes: Then the wiſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>an ſhal not haue compaſſion but ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>de, but ſhall profite borne for a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on helpe, and a publike vtility, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f he ſhal reache a porcion vnto euerye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne. Yet we, as it is declared, do vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erſtande compaſſion a vertue, vnto which Chriſte encourageth vs after the example of his heauenly father, and his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wne in the .6. of Luke, which can be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>owned ſufficiently with no praiſes at any ſeaſon: and truely is highly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to vs in holy Scriptures. For what earthly wight can at the leaſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue in minde, much leſſe depaint in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racion the infinite mercy of God the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and Chriſte our Sauiour? This vertue exalteth a manne to bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. Chriſt calleth the merciful <hi>Beatos,</hi> bleſſed, becauſe they ſhal receyue mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, in the .5.9. &amp; .12. of Mathew, of whom Cap. 25. ſix duties of mercy breefely are propounded.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:19634:53"/>
               <head>Of liberality, and vices con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to this, Auarice and Prodigality. Cap. xxv.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Icero in his firſt booke of offices maketh liberality the other braunch of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, the which ſame he termeth both bountiful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, &amp; alſo benignity, the which ſeemeth not vnhandeſomly in this place to bée annected to the former parts of Iuſtice. For althoughe this vertue is placed in geuing, not as they in reſtoring what is due (whiche ſame ſeemeth to be proper vnto Iuſtice) yet becauſe it ſpreadeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brode her ſelfe vnto others, as Iuſtice doth, eke conſidereth the vtility of men, it ſhal be leiful to ſituate it amonge the members of Iuſtice. Liberality may be defined, a beneficiall good will to gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tify, or els a liberal deſire to merite wel of ſom perſon. This is conuerſaunte (as Cicero telleth) in the vſe of Money, the which to beſtowe honeſtly, and as it
<pb facs="tcp:19634:54"/> oughte with a frée and godly minde, is proper to liberality. For firſte of all a franke conſent of the geuer is required, leſſe throughe an opinion of profite the mind be reſtreigned from doing good.</p>
               <p>Therfore we muſte geue, by reaſon we knowe it to be acceptable vnto God, waiting for no rewarde. We muſte deale wittely when the cauſe and time ſhall poſtulate, to him on whom the gift is worthely beſtowed, which wil not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe the ſame vnto deſtruction, either his owne, or els of others: and we muſt geue part of our proper goods, not of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other mans. For liberality oughte to diſcommodity no man, but profit them as are worthye of a benefite: And we muſt geue according to the worthineſſe of eche one, and deſerte, and rather to a needy creature, than a rich Carle: not as much as perchaunce thou wouldeſt, but ſo muche as thou maiſt, leaſt liberalitie turne into the vice of outragious ſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge, and thou afterwardes beginne to want, and be trobleſom to thy friends: and loſe pleaſure, who is the companion of vertue, and contrarywiſe reteyne ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row
<pb facs="tcp:19634:54"/> the leaguefellow of viciouſnes. And albeit riche men can with leſſe trauaile perfourm the duty of liberality, yet the leſſe hability may alſo become liberall: whoſe bountious good wil ought more to be conſidered, than the benefite it ſelfe. Cicero in his ſecond booke of duties doth ratify two ſortes of liberality. One through which any man ſuccoureth him who néedeth with Argente: The other by which he aideth with trauel or coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel. There be two vices vnlike to libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality, couetouſnes and niggardſhip, and prodigality and riotouſnes: of which ſhe is the defecte of liberality, but this y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, bexwixt which vices liberalitie is ſituated. Auarice is defined, a ſuperfluus gredineſſe of money, which being cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded together carefully for their auaile y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vnſaciable perſons do pleaſure neither <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hemſelues nor others: which very wel <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s termed in the ſanctified Scriptures, <hi>Omnium malorum radix,</hi> the roote of al miſchiefes, out of whiche, felonies, rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beries, deſpoilinges, deceipts, bewray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inges, diſcords, hurly burlyes do ſpring. <hi>Et quid non mortalia pectora cogis auri
<pb facs="tcp:19634:55"/> ſacrafames?</hi> and what dooſt not thou de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtable hunger of gold enforce mennes harts to do? The deſire of mony is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaciable, and a cruell Dropſy: of whom the more that the waters are ſupped vp the more they are thriſted for, <hi>Nam creſcit amor numini quantum ipſa pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunia creſcit,</hi> for the loue of money in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeth, as muche as money her ſelfe doth increaſe. This bondage is altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther moſte wretched, and moſt vile, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies carefull, at all times fearfull, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer quiet, at no time content. Contrary to the vice of Auarice is exceſſe whiche commonly they term prodigality: which ſame likewiſe is a vice, and reſiſteth li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berality. For as the couetous man is ouer gredy in receyuing and reteyning, ſo contrary wiſe the prodigall perſon paſſeth a meane in geuinge. Therfore prodigality may be defined, an immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate largeſſe, and committed vpon no iuſt cauſe. This perdy is vicious, yet may be reuoked more eaſely vnto libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality, than auarice: by reaſon ſhe is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed to profit others, this no man, and not ſo much truely the very poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>our:
<pb facs="tcp:19634:55"/> vnto this oftimes youth is hurtful to the other old age. Moderate expence in like manner, as liberalitie is pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced betweene two vices, vnmeaſurable riot &amp; couetouſneſſe. Herehence a pinch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peny, or els a thrifty felowe, neither is called prodigall, nor yet a niggard.</p>
               <p>Sauing is defyned, a diligent laying vp of thoſe thinges which are gotten, and a guidinge of expenſes. Wherof there ſpringes a Prouerbe, <hi>Magnum Vecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal parſimonia,</hi> Sparinge is a greate reuenew.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="chapter">
               <head>Of Magnificence. Cap. xxvi.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Agnificence ſeemeth to be vnited to liberalitie, which is no other thyng, than a certaone larger bountuouſneſſe, whiche is defined of Cicero, an handlyng or ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of great &amp; excellent mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ers with a certaine honourable, &amp; fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us intent: Herehence co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth a ſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uous a notable man, &amp; he who worketh
<pb facs="tcp:19634:56"/> wounderous feates. This vertue is not belonging vnto poore men, whiche can not performe mightie and miraculous matters, but vnto rich men, as to kings and Princes: of whome yet it is to be taken heede of, that they be not incenſed more through the deſier of vayne glory than vertue, neither principally regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the good will of God, nor paſſynge for the commoditie of men, leſſe they wade beyonde meaſure with their coſt and adminiſtracion in enterpriſing gor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious actes. For alſo there be two vices repugnant to this vertue, the one which is called <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a worke of a baſe courage: and a beggerly magnificence, whiche is of kinne to auarice: the other <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> that is to wit an vnruly ſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſneſſe, &amp; riot, which accordeth with prodigalitie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="chapter">
               <head>Of Freendſhip. Cap. xxvij.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Monge the parts of Iuſtice, Freendſhip alſo is to be nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred: wherof ſith Ariſtotle, and after him Cicero copi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly
<pb facs="tcp:19634:56"/> haue diſputed, we will here breif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly touche thoſe thinges which appeare neceſſarie. Therfore, as Cicero telleth, in his firſt booke <hi>De Legibus,</hi> all the force of Freendſhip is in the agréement of willes, ſtudies and opinions: and in <hi>Laelius:</hi> Freendſhip (ſayth he) is no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thyng than a perfecte accorde of all diuine and humain affayres, with bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolence and fauour: whiche he calleth the ayde of vertues geuen of Nature, not a companion of vices: And the ſame nominated of loue, and begunne of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute her ſelfe: That wee may vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande loue to be naturall, by whiche men are vnited together amonge them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>elues. And becauſe (as alſo wee haue knowen by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ſcriptures, by which the lawe of nature is approued in this cauſe) one man oweth good wil and loue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o another, whereas alſo al other liuing Creatures may appeare to mayntayne freendſhip in their kind, or els ſurely to preſerue beneuolence: it can not bee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oubted, but that fréendeſhip is to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erred vnto Iuſtice, which alſo is verie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eceſſary for the vſe of life, and contey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth
<pb facs="tcp:19634:57"/> the common wealth. What be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neuolence doth differ from friendſhip. Ariſtotle teacheth in the .v Chapiter of his .ix. booke that alſo we may be vnited in good wil with them, whom we do not know, and that the ſame may be ſecret, that it cannot be freendeſhip: and that beneuolence is the Original and Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of amity. By whoſe Sentence freendſhip is thus defyned. That it be an euident beneuolence. Freendſhip is double. One true and ſincere, and proceeding of vertue, which is emonge good men. The other forged, and vulger which is two folde, for either it is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured throughe profit, or els throughe good will. The end than of true freend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip is, Honeſtie, of the counterfayted, profite or pleaſure. Pleaſure ioigneth together children and young folkes.</p>
               <p>Profite yoketh together marchauntes and ſuche like: but vertue bindeth good men, who be friendes indeede, and alſo do perſiſt after death, but they loue for a time. True frendſhip than becauſe it ariſeth out of vertue, can not be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge wicked perſones, as betwixt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19634:57"/> theeues, robbers, ſpoylers, traitours, conſpiratours: albeit ſomewhiles they may appeare fettered together with a moſte ſtraighte bonde, neither alſo is it ſure inoughe amonge them, who are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual neither in maners, nor in exerciſe, nor in wil nor in opinions, nor in riches (althoughe theſe do not alwaies hinder amity, like as nether the age) nor yet in ſtatelines. Emong Princes and their fréends the gloſing of certain Courtiers doth welnie extinguiſhe amitie, appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinge all matters of their gouernours, both ſayings and doinges although they be fooliſh, whiles they get gaine, promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and fauour. The freendſhip then amonge equals is ſtronger, &amp; more ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere, vnited together through conſent of mindes, both willinge and nillinge, one thinge, whom alſo a like ſtudy doth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lite. But this freendeſhip cannot be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt many: that narrow bonde is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaining to few: what manner of one wee reade to haue flouriſhed emongſte them, of whiche ſcarcelye foure or fiue partes are reckened, and perhappes it ſhould be a difficult matter to trace out
<pb facs="tcp:19634:58"/> more, of whom truly it may be verified <hi>Amicus alter idem,</hi> a fréende an other ſame, or one as like as it were the ſelfe ſame perſon, of which two there ought to be one minde. Although verily good men often times haue many fréendes, and wiſh wel vnto thoſe, of whom they the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues likewiſe are entirely beloued yet they communicate that cheefeſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of minds and good wils, and ſtudies onely with one or two, or els ſurely w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> very few. That true friendſhip is very ſeldome, what one was betwixte thoſe fewe copartners of vnfained fréendes, and ſo many times renowned. Becauſe perdie fréendſhip iſſueth of loue, and the degrees of Loue are diuers, likewiſe more degrees of fréendſhip are to be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed. Of which the firſte is, of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, and Children: the ſecond, of bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and Kinſfolke, the third of benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial perſons and Citizens: the laſt of all men. Yet ſomewhiles that ſincere friendſhip which is of a fewe, doth farre exceede al the amities of al men, yea of the very parentes &amp; children, what loue that was betwixt <hi>Pylades</hi> and <hi>Oreſtes, D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19634:58"/> and <hi>Pythias:</hi> concernynge whome reade <hi>Valerius Maximus</hi> the .iiii. booke and vii. Chapiter. This true friendſhip ſurely is not ſodainly made perfect, but ſhe hath her degrees: tyll at lengthe through longe vſe of loue ſittinge in the ſecret Cabane of the hart, and through greate acquaintaunce, and amiable fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhippe it be confirmed. Wherfore they ſay that he is to be elected, whom thou wilt loue: geuing to wit thereby, that we entertaine not any one haſtily into freendſhip without election, whom afterwardes we may forſake with like foolehardines for a trifle, leſſe we apere rather with a certaine rage of loue, then with good aduiſe to haue ben broughte vnto freendſhip. That ſuch a vice may be eſchewed, we oughte to be ſlowe to ioigne in amity, and conſtant to reteine it. Therfore all theſe thinges are to be taken heede of, which are wont to wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken freendſhips: as contentions, bitter brawlinges, deſpites, waywardneſſe, wrath, enuy, emulacion, and ſuch like.</p>
               <p>But to admoniſh without ſharpneſſe, and to bee admoniſhed, is proper to
<pb facs="tcp:19634:59"/> friendſhippe. Neither truly is it to be thought, that thoſe friendes any where be found among men, which althoughe there be one like conſente of willes and ſtudies for the moſt part) may not ſome whiles ſeme to be put in reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>braunce, if they ſhall any whit offend: and alſo it ought to be denied theſe, if they aſke any thinge, which can not be accompliſhed honeſtly and godly. For honeſt matters are to be requeſted of friendes, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt cauſes are to be don for the friends ſake. Rather perdy then being deſired we ſhould committe filthy thinges, we ſhall permit the friendſhip, which pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentely ceaſeth to be true, by litle and litle throughe ſlackneſſe of vſe to be mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, and to vaniſh away. For that which is ſodainely broken of, appeareth neuer to haue ben true. But yet this ſame ſeperacion is to be auoyded as much as may be. For neither muſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man ſo loue, as though ſomtimes he ſhould be at a defiaunce. Harty loue that whiche the ſacred Scriptures do approue, commendeth perfecte friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, by which we are willed to loue our
<pb facs="tcp:19634:59"/> neighbour no leſſe than our ſelues. There ought then to be an indifferent beneuolence of eche others mind. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is it to be required, that the one ſhoulde more fancy the other than him ſelfe. And of frendſhip ſurely hether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to. Enmite reſiſtethe this, the moſte greeuous plague of humayn kinde, and which maketh men worſe then beaſts, and deſpoileth them of all humanitie.</p>
               <p>For a man ought to be deare vnto a man, ſith he may ſee beaſtes of one ſort to be coupled together amonge them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues. And as friendſhip maketh men courteous and gratefull, ſo doth hatred cauſe them cruel and odious: and as ſhe doth very much recreate the ſprites, ſo is this not a litle troubleſome bothe to her ſelf, and others, &amp; the cauſe of many miſchiefes. Herehence ſpryng ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, herehence proceede Murthers, herehence commeth all crueltie. For whom any man hateth, he wiſheth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, and the caytife doth wofully crucifie himſelfe through a luſt to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge, and a deſier to hurt, the mynde a tormentour brandiſſhynge a ſecret
<pb facs="tcp:19634:60"/> whip, as Iuuenall ſaith: where as in holy Scriptures it is manifeſt, <hi>Homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidam eſſe quiſquis fratrem ſuu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> oderit:</hi> That be is a man killer, whoſoeuer ſhal hate his brother. Wherefore all enmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie is to be auoyded, cake diligently it is to be taken heede, that wee miniſter not a cauſe of contempt to any man and if an occaſion be geuen, it is to be labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by all poſſibilitie that he be reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to vs, who was eſtraunged or fallen from vs. If ſo be that by chaunce wee ſhall hate any one, who may ſeeme to haue iniured vs, yet we ought to beare in minde that wee are Chriſtians, that wee forgeue, and put away anger and hatred, waytyng for the like facilitie of remiſſion at Gods hand, which ſo many times wee haue experimented. No ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilitie truly is more greeuous, than battel: no greater alienation, and ſepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racion of mindes, none more pernicious none more fierſe, and through whiche more may breake forth violently with more bitter hatreds into mutuall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, and ſo furiouſly ſomewhiles may be incenſed that not only Citizens
<pb facs="tcp:19634:60"/> but alſo very brothers and kinſemen are brought in contencious turmoyles among themſelues, fighting for life and death, ignorant of their aliaunce, infla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with common madneſſe, and now puttyng aparte al humanitie clad them ſelues with the crueltie of beaſtes. And albeit battell of it ſelfe, neither ought properly to be ſayde good, nor euill, ſith it may iuſtly be vſed, and ought alſo ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily to be taken in hand ſomtimes, eſpecially if it be attempted in ſuche ſorte vpon lawfull occaſion, that it be a defence of Iuſtice, &amp; be referred to that parte whiche is termed <hi>Vindicatio,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uengement: Yet whereas the conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of bothe enemies may not be a like iuſtfull, it appeareth not that any battel can be executed, vnto whom on the one parte Iniuſtice may not be annected.</p>
               <p>Wherefore it is not to be enterpriſed raſhly of potentates to whom the title of Warfare is committed, nor yet, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe for a right and a neceſſarie cauſe: as if the thinges vniuſtfully taken from vs ſhould be fetched agayne, if iniurie were to be wreaked, or violence to be
<pb facs="tcp:19634:61"/> repreſſed: let it be proclaymed, and let it be referred vnto that ende, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyng els appeare to haue been mente through battel, than peace ſought for, or enquired. Wee muſt cheifly beware, as much as may be, that we wax not cruel toward innocentes, and the feble ſorte, and ſuppliaunt people: that all thinges be not waſted with ſworde and fier: That more damage be not doone to our friendes, than to our enemies: That battell be not wittingly and greedely taken in hande, which cannot be perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trated without crueltie. There be alſo other vices contrarie to friendſhip, as teſtifneſſe of minde, as Flattery a gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous peſtilence to amitie, vnmeete for a liberall diſpoſicion, not muche hurtfull and daungerous to the wary, and to the glorious and ſimple, becauſe it is a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie enmitie, whiche diſprofiteth with a flatteryng grace, ſeruily commendinge him who is preſent, and wrongfully car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping and deridyng him which is abſent: whom Terence doth elegantly &amp; feate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſet out in colours in the ſeconde Acte and ſeconde Scene in <hi>Eunuchus.</hi> Vnto
<pb facs="tcp:19634:61"/> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oth is flatterie alike miſerable, both vnto him whiche ſpeaketh al thinges for anothers pleaſure, &amp; alſo to him whiche admitteth this ill fauored ſugred ſpéech of one that vpholdeth his yea and nay in euery cauſe: but that he is a moſte vile bondeſlaue, and this a Nodgecocke, who perceiueth not him ſelfe to be a laughing ſtocke. And of Iuſtice, and of her braunches ſufficiently it is re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oned.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="chapter">
               <head>Of Iniustice. Cap. xxviij.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Niuſtice is contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to Iuſtice, which beynge adioygned perdy to al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> partes of Iuſtice, now ſhal bee debated ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what more at large</p>
               <p>As Iuſtice yeldeth to euery man his owne, ſo dothe Iniuſtice hale vnto her ſelfe, what is due vnto others. And as before we haue diuided Iuſtice, ſo ſhall it be leifull, alſo to ſeuour Iniuſtice.</p>
               <p>Firſt and formoſte into common and
<pb facs="tcp:19634:62"/> priuate, and this into diſtributinge and chaunging: Secondly, as we haue tolde the partes of Iuſtice, religion, godlynes and others: ſo may the members of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtice be repeted ſuperſticion, impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and moe which briefly we haue deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criued: Only in preſence we wil make manifeſt the percels and common and priuate wronge. Common Iniuſtice compriſeth two formes: One which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth ordinaunce: the other whiche repungneth equitie: the lawes are vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated, when as either through niggard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines, or the contempt of men, or els for ſom other occaſion holſom decrees, and ſtatutes are inuerted, or abrogated, or vnrightfulye wreſted, and weakened with counterfet interpretacions.</p>
               <p>Equity is defiled, when as not onely the wordes of law are recited and wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed ſubtilly, but the vnderſtandinge and euenneſſe the very ſoule of the law is neglected, and the Prouerb winneth place <hi>Sumu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ius, ſumma iniuria,</hi> extreme law, extreme wrong: as if the Iudges, or Lawyers ſhoulde be corrupted with gifts, or diſtempered w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the affections of
<pb facs="tcp:19634:62"/> loue or hatred. Theſe matters alſo are debated of Rhetoricians in the Chapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>De ſtatu ſcripti et voluntatis.</hi> There are two parts of priuate iuſtice: againſt whome likewiſe two maye be layde. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>niuſtè diſtribuens</hi> and <hi>iniuſtè commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ns,</hi> wrongfully diſtributinge and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſtly exchaunging. Wrongfully diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buting doth fauour the wicked, doth not defend the good, them ſhe exalteth, theſe ſhe preſſeth downe: ſhe preferreth flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers and lewde perſonnes before the ſimple and honeſt: ſhe more eſtéemeth nobility and riches, than vertue and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pience. Vniuſtly exchaunging doth not reſtore what is due, ſhe deceiueth them with whom ſhe ioigneth in byinge, ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and in concluding other contractes eſpecially in guage and confederacie: ſhe deuiſeth titles of poſſeſſions: ſhe ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth pleaſure by long practiſe in things procured by couine: ſhe trauaileth to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>miniſh common and publike commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ies, and out of theſe to adde ſomwhat her ſelfe: To conclude, ſhe leaueth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t vnto euery man his owne. Doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e of all theſe partes of Iniuſtice In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurie
<pb facs="tcp:19634:63"/> is the mother, which is don, either to the common wealth, or els to al men, either in violatinge the lawes, or els ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in diſtributinge, or exchaunginge vniuſtly.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="chapter">
               <head>Of Fortitude. Cap. xxix.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E haue diſputed of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and Iuſtice: it en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſueth that mencion bee made of Fortitude. For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude may be defined. A cuſtome, or els an af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of the minde, whiche taketh in hande premeditated daungers, and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boures, and ſuſteineth what euer inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities do chaunce, repelling timidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and anger. Of Cicero it is defined an affection of the minde, pacient in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenturinge peril, and in trauell and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row whoſe principall duties he wil that there be two, a contempte of death and ſorow: becauſe all valiante courage is tried, either in wofulneſſe, or in labour, or in daunger, and in the vndertakinge and putting to flight of dreadefull mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.
<pb facs="tcp:19634:63"/> The Stoikes define Fortitude, a vertue contending for equity. <hi>Chriſippus</hi> an affection of the minde, in ſufferinge and ſuſteyning, yelding vnto extreame law without feare. Manly courage ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to bee ingendred partely of will, partly of the faculty of the angry ſoule, becauſe the operacion of Fortitude re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth ſome commocion hereof: who notwithſtanding her ſelfe is voluntary and is buſied in the ſuffering of ſorow, and in aduenturing of perilles: and the will ought to rule, but that rage ought to be obeyſant vnto deſire and counſell. Fortitude is conuerſant in reſtreining of fearefull matters, both cauſing timi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>itie of ſom daunger aboute to hurt, and alſo the expectation of perill, as it were in the matter wherin ſhe is exerciſed, whether it be in Marcial prowes, or els in Domeſtical troubles, that at laſt ſhe may obtaine that vttereſt good: This vertu (as likewiſe the reſidew) is a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diocrity betwixte ouermuch and to litle that is to witte, betweene timidity and boldneſſe, whiche vices after what fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion they may be eſchewed. Horace ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poundeth in theſe Verſes.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19634:64"/>
               <q>
                  <l>In neede appere stoute and ſtronge: be thou vviſe</l>
                  <l>To ſhrinke in thy ſayles beginning to riſe.</l>
               </q>
               <p>The dutie of Fortitude is double, to aduenture, and to ſuſtaine daungers &amp; aduerſities with that minde y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it maye content God, and obay his commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, for whoſe ſake all things ought to be done, and doubtleſſe to enter on them, and to abide them not only coura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſly and manfully, but alſo prude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly is the parte of a valiant man: for ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhould he take in hande any thynge vnaduiſedly and harebraynly, and with no conſideration, leſſe he may ſeem ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be allured with violent moode, than with perfect reaſon. Vnto Forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude true and ſincere, &amp; adorned with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vertues. Ariſtotle hath annected in his thirde booke <hi>Ad Nicomachu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> other fiue fourmes not abſolute, yet as of kinne. The firſt of Citizens fighting for their countrie: The ſeconde of Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours
<pb facs="tcp:19634:64"/> who by Marciall policie do aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture perils: the thirde of them whiche truſt vnto experience: the fourthe of them which trauell through an hope to winne: the fifte of ſuch as haue al their affiaunce in Fortune, neither ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly examininge the daungers, whom ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance cauſeth ſturdie. Verely it is no leſſe the parte of Fortitude to ſuffer ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamitie, to ſuſteine iniurie, to bridell the moodes of minde with an vpright and conſtant courage, than to hazarde the life, to contempne death, and doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe with harte and will to die, if ſo he ſhall purpoſe to pleaſe God. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Fortitude is conuerſant either in the receiuyng of daungers, or els in the enduring: vnto this vertue foure four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes are ſubnected, Confidence &amp; mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naminitie whiche perteine vnto recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing. Pacience and Perſeuerance who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e referred vnto enduring: The two <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t belonge as it were to the firſt mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n of Fortitude, the latter to the ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ance, and ſtableneſſe and conſtancie of euils. Of all theſe perfect manlineſſe doth conſiſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:19634:65"/>
               <head>Of Confidence and Magna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimitie. Cap. xxx.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Onfidence (ſaith Cicero) is a ſure truſt of minde: either by which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> minde hath planted in her ſelfe much beleif in weightie and honeſt matters, with a ſure hope. And vnto this Boldeneſſe appeareth to be of aliance, and yet it is a vice: ſith it is led not with counſell and iudgement, as Fortitude, vnto whom Prudency is a perpetuall companion, but with vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence and temeritie: not taking ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent aduiſe, before it geue the aſſaulte on daungers, whether it may ouercome: and how it may, and whether it be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt to vndertake the ſame. But confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence doth not aduenture ieoperdies ſtoutely and with a great truſt, vnleſſe diligently premeditated afore. For they are not to be iudged ſtronge men who dare to aduenture leſſe, but they which commonſtrate a moderate vertue of minde, whom reaſon ought to rule, and
<pb facs="tcp:19634:65"/> make agreeable to vertue. Contarie to confidence is miſtruſt, a lowe abaſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente of the minde, the ſame which diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peire is, which aboue we haue compen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diouſly touched in the chapiter of deſire and hope. Magnanimity is an ample<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of a noble, and an vnconquerable ſtomacke, and a might and ſtoutneſſe to commit valiaunt actes. This ſuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth confidence, and as an helper dothe fortify her being of kinne. Vnderſtand you a noble corage, not a proud, neither an arrogant, but a modeſt, and keepinge vnder foote inſolencye, very noble, and contemninge worldely vanities. For this vertue is principallye tryed in the contempte both of thoſe great matters whiche the gréedy common people hath in wonderfull admiration: and alſo in the repreſſing of perturbations, that all ambicion, niggardlineſſe, and concupiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence may be reſiſted with a triu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>phing courage, that al aduerſities may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantely endured. Cicero in his firſte booke of duties, doth teache that there are two partes of the greatneſſe of cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage; of the whiche one is tried in proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perity,
<pb facs="tcp:19634:66"/> the other in aduerſity: becauſe neither tribulation is of ſtrength to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage a noble ſtomack, nor the riches of fortune of power to make him preſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous. Contrary vnto Magnanimitie be two vices, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſuperfluous hau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines, either a proud and ſwelling mind: and <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a want or defect of cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage. In the firſt vice is conteyned an auaunting, extolling it ſelfe inſolentely and foolyſhly, and a minde ſtrouting out vnwiſely: what one is of Thraſo in Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence a vaine and peeuiſh perſonne, and blind with ouermuch loue of him ſelfe, than which nothing can be excogitated more fooliſh, whome no good and modeſt man may be able to abide. This ſect of companions is odious vnto all ſortes, ſaue only vnto paraſites. Repugnant to this vice is that other which is called <hi>Demiſsio animi,</hi> lacke of corage, vſually tearmed <hi>Puſillanimitas</hi> cowardiſe, that is to ſay, a foule and an vnſeemely faint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of courage, fléeing imminent daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and vilainouſly languiſhing in large and wonderful exploits, what one hath béene of Effemynate perſonnes, as of
<pb facs="tcp:19634:66"/> 
                  <hi>Sardanapalus,</hi> who verelye not reſiſtinge, banniſhed from his Empire, concluded hs owne deſtruction through a preuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted deſpeire: as of <hi>Heliogabalus,</hi> as of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, who beinge enfeebled with plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures haue led a ſlouthfull and a beaſtly life. To them which wente afore may be adioyned, a deſire of good eſtimacion, of which in like manner theare are two vices: the one inordinate ſute, the other a contempt of Fame and reputacion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="chapter">
               <head>Of Pacience and Perſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce. Cap. xxxi.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Acience Cicero defineth, a vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary, and a longe permiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of hard and difficulte mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters for honeſties ſake or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite: that is to witte, a ſtable and a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtante ſufferaunce of humian thynges, through which wée ſuſtaine what euer aduerſity ſhall chaunce vnto vs with a pacient minde. He called it voluntary, becauſe this vertue, as alſo Magnani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, is ſituated in will, which that an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry
<pb facs="tcp:19634:67"/> faculty of the Soule doth helpe.</p>
               <p>That it is added of him, for honeſties ſake: hee propoundeth the ende of this vertue, which alſo is apperteining vnto all the reſt. For if laboures be ſuſtey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned not for Vertue, but either by reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of hatred, or riches, or honoures, he ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth it an horrible aſperity, which imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tateth pacience. But of vs at al ſeaſons y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> marke is to be appointed, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our doing pleaſe God, vnto whom vertue is accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table. The charge of pacience is dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: One in abidyng Iniuries receiued: The other in ſuffringe all caſualities of Fortune with an vpright minde. Hee ouercommeth who beareth Iniury, by reaſon bothe he vanquiſheth him ſelfe, and his aduerſary, ſithe he repelleth the affection: Hee is broughte in bondage, who doth iniury, becauſe he yeeldeth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to affections, and is ſurmounted of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and gréedineſſe. He is iuſt, this fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe vniuſte. It is the parte then of a pacie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t man, both to conquere iniury by contemninge, and not to take reuenge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of it to him ſelfe, but to commit it vnto God, vnto whom it belongeth to
<pb facs="tcp:19634:67"/> chaſtice Iniquities, and to receiue all chaunce with an egall minde, to endure pouerty, banniſhment, barrennes, wée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, and wailing, reproche, deſpite, ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitude, gréeuous diſeaſes, blindnes, and if any thing alſo be more wretched; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to deſpeire, neuer to be diſcouraged through calamities. For whereas the life of man is ful of miſeries, and diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, who had not ſome whiles rather to leaue his life (as, certaine curſed Imphs &amp; daſtardes haue dun) eake at one time to cloſe vp all his cares, then alwaies to leade a peineful life: except he being Haruaiſed with the breſt plate of paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, would valiauntly gaineſet a redy and an vnuincible courage to abide all thinges to the ende, and would recken any life well to be paſſed ouer, vertue being his guide? Som haue falſly ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed them to be ſtrong, who in deſperate caſes haue wilfully murthered them ſelues, eſchewing either beggery, or ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominy, or captiuity, or bondage, or not ſuſtaining loue, or els auoydinge any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther calamity: whome Ariſtotle more rightfully iudged to be niſe and woman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh:
<pb facs="tcp:19634:68"/> ſithens it is the guiſe of a ſtedfaſt and a valiaunt perſon to take any For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune in good worth: but the property of a timorous and a ſluggiſh to miſtruſte, and to be diſmaide with laboures, and ſhamefully to faint in courage. Impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cience may be ſaide a vice repugnaunt to pacience, an eſchewinge of an honeſt peine and ſorrowe: whoſe nature it is not a perplexed matter to vnderſtande by thoſe things which preſently are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared. There are ſome vnſufferable who feare trauels, others who flee wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullneſſe: and thinke them intollerable which pacie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce learneth to be ſuſtained.</p>
               <p>They do yeelde vnto turmoiles, theſe are crucified with paſſions, and cares, &amp; do abide iniury hardly and gréeuouſly.</p>
               <p>There be ſome likewiſe who are not able moderatly inough to vſe their proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perity, whoſe mindes are to much puf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed vp with the inſolencie of their good eſtate: as muche to be diſcommended as they, becauſe it is a thing, no leſſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſéemely to be diſcomfited, then péeuiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to triumphe. Perſeueraunce is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined of Cicero, a ſtable, and a perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all
<pb facs="tcp:19634:68"/> abode in reaſon vprightly examined.</p>
               <p>This is a faithfull companion for paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and an ayde in bearing aduerſity, and in moderatinge proſperity with e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qualitie, and in brideling all the ſurges of the mind, and bringing them in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection to the diſcourſe of reaſon. For a puiſſaunt ſtomacke, as he ſaieth, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out conſtancie and honeſt moderacion of minde, is nothing worth, waueringe or lightneſſe and an vnſtable gouerme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of humaine affaires is a Vice contrary vnto perſeueraunce: which either for a womanlines of mind doth vnaduiſedly geue place vnto difficulties, nor is of ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficacie to endure vexacions: or elles by reaſon of an obſtinacie continueth in his opinion arrogantely and ſtubburnely, which reaſon co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeth to chaunge.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="chapter">
               <head>Of the Vyces betvveene vvhich Fortitude is placed. Cap. xxxij.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:19634:69"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Ortitude is the meane be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt two vices, boldnes and timidity. Boldneſſe is an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduiſed enterpriſe of perils, or els a raſhe confidence, by which any man not payſing his hability dothe aduenture daunger with a blinde inuaſion, either through the ignoraunce of the difficulty, or through the loftines of ſtomacke and deſire of renowne, or through diſpaire, or els doutles through a daſtardlineſſe and madnes ranſacking the mind. This vice is farre diſſonant from Fortitude, becauſe it geueth not reaſon and counſell. This alſo is repo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed aboue among the affections; by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon it ſtirreth vp the rage of the minde to worke Hairebrainely and aduentu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly. To this miſchiefe the repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunt vice is Timidity, through which any one without occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is perced with terrour, and feared with any creaking, and dreadeth thoſe thinges which are valiantly to be enterpriſed for vertue: A daſtarde, an effeminate perſon, and one not able to abide honeſt toyle: who whiles he is ouer carefull for his life, he
<pb facs="tcp:19634:69"/> ſhunneth not ſhame, and diſworſhippe, which eſpecially is to be auoided. Of either vice otherwiſe it is debated in the explicacion of affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in this place, in which not the affection, but a vicious property contrarious to manlineſſe is to be vnderſtanded.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="chapter">
               <head>Of Temperaunce. Cap. xxxiii.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Emperaunce is a vertue which ſubdueth pleſures vnto the dominio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. The ſame is defined of Cicero, a firme and a temperate rule of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ouer luſte, and other euil braides of the minde. It is alſo termed a mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of deſires, obedient to reaſon: and in another place, the gouerneſſe of all commocions, it is conuerſaunt in refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of pleaſures, as the ſame Aucthor agreeth with Plato and Ariſtotle. In Gréeke, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, whiche our country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man calleth both Temperaunce, and
<pb facs="tcp:19634:70"/> Modeſtie, and alſo Frugalitie. For it is occupied in refraynynge delices, and deſiers, as in the matter, whereof it intreateth: And becauſe ſome plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures are naturall, and common to all liuynge creatures: others conſiſting in opinion: and they bothe either of the minde or of the body: of which ſome are good, whiche are referred vnto a good ende: others vicious, whiche are direc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to an ill: this vertu is familiar with good and honeſt men: it abſteyneth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the contrarie: verely it bridleth al con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcencies with the iudgement of reaſon: whiche Seneca confirmeth in theſe wordes: Temperance ruleth pleaſures: ſome it hateth and driueth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, with others it diſpenſeth, &amp; tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to an holſom faſhion. By whiche wordes it is to be vnderſtanded that this is a vertue very well acquainted with Prudencie. Sith than Tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce is buſied in meaſurynge of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petites, her firſt charge is, to contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plate, what the neceſſitie of nature may poſtulate for to paſſe the life com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modiouſly, that ſhe may ſatiſfie her,
<pb facs="tcp:19634:70"/> who is contented with few thynges, whereby the ſuperfluous vſe of thinges naturall may be eſchewed, and may be reteined within the bounde of Nature, The other is, that when as now ſhe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ath vnquiſſhed the delightes of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, ſhe conquere alſo the paſſions of the minde ſtrugling agaynſt reaſon, that ſhe keepe vnder arrogancie, that ſhe know her ſelfe, that ſhe ſtifely repine ſenſualitie, and indeuour by little and little to brynge it in ſeruitude to Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. Thrée partes are annected of Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cero vnto Temperance: Continence, Clemencie, and Modeſtie. Of whiche the firſt doth gouerne Luſt through the rule of Counſell: The other remitteth Hatred: The thirde preſerueth honeſt ſhamefaſtneſſe, and demureneſſe, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out whiche nothinge can be accompted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ight.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:19634:71"/>
               <head>Of Continence and Absti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nence. Cap. xxxiiij.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Etwixt Continence and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinence that appeareth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly to bee the difference, that Continence doeth guide affections, and kepeth a meane in al or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of liuing and trimming, and eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally (as Cicero beareth witneſſe) in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſlippinge of pleaſures: vnto whom Incontinence is repugnant. Abſtinence repreſſeth the handes from other mens goods, vnto whom Rauenie is appoſite. This is in an innocent man, the in a te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate: Continence is defined of him, a vertue by which the greedineſſe is ruled through the gouerment of counſell. It is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to deſire, to pleaſure, to luſt. For the charge hereof is, to moderate all appetites, luſt, riotte, drunkenneſſe, gluttuous, deuouringe of meates, and to cauſe all ſences and delices obedient to reaſon. This vertu not only maketh men commendable, &amp; rulers of deſires, but alſo vncorrupted, and iocant, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo
<pb facs="tcp:19634:71"/> neate to conclude verye excellent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> matters: But contrarywiſe of intem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perancie growe many kindes of diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, the paunche burdened with ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much meate and drinke, doth both peſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the minde and darken the reaſon.</p>
               <p>But yet that ſcope euermore oughte to bee propoſed vnto all men, that they reſtraine them ſelues therfore, becauſe they ought to know by ſo doing to pleaſe God, whom they muſt ſerue, not by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon it aduauntageth the healthe. For if any man dothe auoyde incontinencie only for health, or els for vtilities ſake, be meriteth not guardon: vnto contine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce may be referred al thoſe vertues, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer appellatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they may haue, which do moderate pleaſures, apparel, liuing, meate, drinke: which make chaſte mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt, and ſober perſonnes: which bridle thoſe abhominable deſtructions, ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluity, vnleyfull appetite, greedyneſſe, drunckenneſſe, and ſuche like, throughe which voluptuous, Lecherous, effemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate gourmanders, drunken men, and worſe than beaſts are made. Through Continence we come vnto the praiſe of
<pb facs="tcp:19634:72"/> Temperaunce. She is perdie rather an vnperfecte vertue than an abſolute, as liketh Ariſtotle: yet very neceſſary for the duty of Temperaunce, a vertue fully accompliſhed. <hi>Celius Calcaguinus</hi> hath intituled in his inquiſicions, that Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotle doth declare in his <hi>Ethikes,</hi> and <hi>Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarchus</hi> in his Commentarie of Morall Vertu, what difference there is betwixt the continent man and vncontynent, Temperate and vntemperate. For the Continent perſon contendeth with af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, and vanquiſheth them: the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>continent perdie doth repine, but beyng ouercommed doth lament. Contrary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the temperate hath no ſtruglyng: but vſeth appeaſed affections, as the calme Sea, whiche is toſſed with no wynde. But the vntemperate without reſiſtynge graunteth vnto perturbaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, take profeſſeth himſelfe willingly conſenting to all delices. The contrary vice vnto Continence, is incontinence, ſpreadyng abrode her braunches egally. She may be defined, An immoderate deſier of pleaſures, which is not gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with the Empyre of Reaſon: ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:19634:72"/> it is a ſuperfluous vſe, and repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to reaſon, of luſt, gluttony, drunk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and other vnſeemely pleaſures. Nothynge is more filthy and vile than this vice, which maketh a man a bounde ſeruante, and deſpoyleth him of al liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: whom it deliuereth in bondage to moſte wanton rulers, as to Deſiers, Luſtes, Fleſhfondynges, Wrathe, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uarice, and ſuche other ſtewardes of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proche &amp; deformitie: as elegantly it is diſputed of Cicero in his firſt Paradox.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="chapter">
               <head>Of Clemencie. Cap. xxxv.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Ven as Continence is tried in the reſtreigninge and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derating of deſiers, ſo is Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencie in the bridlyng of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er. For there are two partes of the Soule, as before it is declared, the deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing, and the angry: out of which all af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ections do proceede: Clemencie is defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed of Cicero, through which the minds <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>naduiſedly enforced to hate one, are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>epreſſed with gentleneſſe. Seneca
<pb facs="tcp:19634:73"/> alledging ſundry definitions of the ſame Vertue ſayeth, Clemencie is a tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the mind in power to reuenge: either, a gentleneſſe of the ſuperiour to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes the inferiour, in ordering of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhementes: either, a bendinge of the minde vnto fauourableneſſe, in exaction of puniſhment. For it is called the ſame pleaſantneſſe, or méekeneſſe, and Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencie, by which the braide of anger is repelled with reaſon, and a modeſty is ſhewed in reuenginge, and chaſtiſing. But wiſdom doth ſo rule her, that ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther all ſhould be pardoned, nor any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> corrected. For both of them rather doth anſwere vnto cruelty, than Clemencie: yet notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding it is better to offend in the more fréendly poynte, than in the contrary: vnleſſe perhappes they who beare office in the common wealth, ſhal ſuppoſe an example néedeful to be prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed on ſome, whom Cicero wiſheth to be like vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawes, who are trained to puniſh, not through anger, but equitie. It is the parte of Clemencie to ſearche out the cauſes of fauouring. Certes no priuate perſon oughte to feare to bende
<pb facs="tcp:19634:73"/> him ſelfe to the more Courtious parte, nether ought to deuiſe at any time how to requite the Iniury inferred to him: but ought to beare vnder foote the incen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinges of choler, &amp; ought to vnderſtande this to be the excellenteſt victory of all others, and chéefely conuenient for a Chriſtian man. Cruelty, and fierſneſſe, or els ſtoutneſſe of the minde in reuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging, and puniſhing, is repugnaunte to Clemencie, whoſe companion is Bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſhneſſe: that is to wit a beſticall hoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tility. Than which two vices nothing is more diuerſe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the nature of man, vnto whome appertaineth Humanitie and Clemencie: and compaſſion ioyned hereto with an amiable bonde, whiche maketh menne gentle and courteous: than whiche no vertue may be more ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to God, whoſe mercye is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meaſurable &amp; vneſtimable. Softneſſe ſeemeth to be of kinne to Clemencie, but it is a vice: whiche is belonginge to an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iotte, not to a man fauourable.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:19634:74"/>
               <head>Of Modestye. Cap. xxxvi.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Odeſtia,</hi> Modeſtie, ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, becauſe it keepeth a certaine meane and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration. Cicero defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth it in his ſecond boke <hi>De Inuencione,</hi> throughe whiche honeſt ſhame doth gette a worthie and a ſtable authority, and in his firſte booke of Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, of all thinges whiche are done, and which are ſaide, an order and a meane, and a knowledge of an oportunity of fit ſeaſones to accompliſh a thing. The Stoykes, a Science of ſettinge thoſe thinges whiche ſhalbe done or ſayde, in their proper places. The firſt definition commendeth vnto vs Honeſt ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtneſſe whiche Cicero termeth a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine natural Timiditie, and a baſhful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, whiche is a certayne reuerende <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eare towardes men: whoſe propertie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s to offende no man: as it belongeth to Iuſtice, to violate no man whiche is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>efined of him in <hi>Particions Oratorye,</hi> the warde of al vertues, eſchewing diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worſhip,
<pb facs="tcp:19634:74"/> and chiefely ſéeking for praiſe.</p>
               <p>And Ariſtotle calleth it a feare of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proche &amp; infamie. And theſe definitions verely ſeeme not to declare one certain vertue ſhamefaſtneſſe, but a certaine generall vnited together with all ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, whiche by another appellacion is called <hi>Decorum</hi> Comlyneſſe. Shame is reherſed of vs among the affections: where wee couet a ſodayne commocion to be vnderſtanded, through which any man is troubled vnwares: but in this place an affection limited to vertue, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by vſe, which through the feare of reproche and infamy calleth vs backe from vices, if we acknowledge it, not as Vertue her ſelfe, yet verily yoked with Vertue. Diogenes named the redneſſe, ingendred of this affection, <hi>Virtutis co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorem</hi> the coloure of Vertue, declaringe that kinde of ſhame to proceede from a good diſpoſicion, which yet in this place wee will to be moderate: that it bee a mediocrity, which is proper to vertues, betwixt ouermuch ſhame and timiditie a counterfayter of baſhfulneſſe and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudencie. Of ſhame a ſhamefaſte or a
<pb facs="tcp:19634:75"/> baſhful man is called by the title of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue: vnto whom is contrarious an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent, and an vnſhamefaſt perſon.</p>
               <p>This feare of diſhoneſte matters is commendable, and in the younger ſorte it ſignifieth a towardneſſe of Vertue, &amp; beſides the eſpeciall ornamente of wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. But Impudency is a deteſtable Vice, by whiche the comelineſſe, and all the honeſty of life is neglected: and an entraunce vnto vices is opened, becauſe they are not feared. The other defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitions of Cicero, which euen now wee haue putte, do ſufficiently declare, what Modeſtie is: that there be an order, and meane conningly to be obſerued of thoſe thinges which are don, and ſaide, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by euery matter may bee excecuted in his proper place and time, &amp; decently.</p>
               <p>For the duty hereof is, ſo to aſſwage the troubleſom moodes, that a certaine harmony of all doynges be obſerued: That nothyng which is fooliſh, &amp; ſcarce ſéemely, either be doone or ſayde, that nothing be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted couetouſly through Enuie, Loue, Luſt, Arrogancie, Ambi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cion, and other vnlawfull appetites.
<pb facs="tcp:19634:75"/> Vnder Modeſtie be placed Lowlineſſe of minde, a deſier to learne, pleaſant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, either delectableneſſe, or ciuilitie of talke, and furniture of body. Lowli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of minde, which they call Humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, is the very notable vertue of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian men: by whiche any man doth ſo preſſe downe the malipertneſſe of cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, that by how much the higher he is, by ſo muche the more lowly he ſhuld behaue himſelfe. Chriſte himſelf would that we learne this vertue of him, who called himſelf meeke, and of an humble and lowe ſpirit: that wee likewiſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordyng to his example ſhoulde extenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate our goods, if there be any: whereas wée can obtaine no good thyng, whiche is not geuen vs by the will and gift of God: that there ſhoulde be no occaſion to any man of braggyng of himſelf, ſith euery perfect gift commeth by inſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from God the Father, who lighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the mindes of men, through Ieſus Chriſte our Sauiour, through whome men haue receiued perfect wiſdom au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoriſed by the benefite of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ghoſt. Therefore this vertue teacheth that
<pb facs="tcp:19634:76"/> eſpecially, which in times paſt was ſaid to fall downe from Heauen <hi>Noſce te ipſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> know thy ſelf: that no man perdy ſhuld attribute ouermuch to himſelf, ſithens he hath nothyng, whiche he hath not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued. This alſo is the charge of a pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent perſon whereby you ſhall vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande Modeſtie and Temperance at al ſeaſons to be very ſtraightly ioyned to Prudencie: wherof alſo ſhe is tearmed of the Greekes <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as it were the Fortreſſe of wiſdome. The contrary vice is arrogancie, throughe which any man blinded with the loue of him ſelfe, faineth many notable thinges to bee in him, which are not in him, and greater than may be in him: either an inſolent and vayne boſtinge, and wantynge the iudgement of the minde. This vice of fooliſh perſons by ouerwéening in them ſelues to well, is hatefull both to God and men. The other parte of Modeſtie is coupled to the former with greate af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitie, the deſier of learnyng, by which any man acknowledgyng his ignorance is holden with the loue of Science, to the procuring of whiche he frameth his
<pb facs="tcp:19634:76"/> minde. He doeth eaſely learne many thinges, who is ſtudious of wiſdom, and vnderſtandeth that he is ignorant in many matters: what fellowes were the Philoſophers, whoſe whole life hath béen nothing els than a certaine perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall ſtudie of knowledge and wiſdom. Contrarie vnto theſe be ſuche, who mought attayne to greate learning vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe they did ſuppoſe themſelues alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to haue ſtored their Pouches: the whiche chiefly repugneth this vertue, whiche proceedeth from Modeſtie and confeſſyon of proper ignorance. This vertue is ſituated betwixt two vices, Curioſitie and careleſneſſe, either neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence of learnynge, and knowledge. Curioſitie is a ſuperfluous paine, or an immoderate greedines to know things either pernicious or vayne, and littel a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayleable: contrarie to the laudable and natiue, and vehement deſier and indeuour to learne ingendred in al men naturally. For the ſerche &amp; inquiſicion of truthe is proper to man. And as ouer muche induſtrious labour is worthely diſprayſed, ſo is negligence, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempte
<pb facs="tcp:19634:77"/> of Science, whiche is appertey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninge to blockiſh and dull perſons, who appeare more like vnto bruite creatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, then to men. The third braunche of Modeſtie is Merineſſe or Pleaſant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and delectableneſſe, and alſo Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manitie, and courteſie of talke, whiche who that ſhall vſe prudently, he ſhalbe pleaſant to all men, and for that alſo the better accepted. Merineſſe is which aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribeth a certaine meane to ſportes and paſtimes: and vſeth theſe ſame in time and place with them, vnto whom they are thankefull, to ſtur vp honeſt mirth, and to wipe away the anguiſhes of the minde with a certayne delight. This alſo is a meane betwixt two vices, as Ariſtotle beareth witneſſe in his ſecond booke <hi>Ad Nicomachum,</hi> vnhoneſt ſkof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fing, and carterlike vnſauourneſſe. He that keepeth a meane of pleaſantneſſe applied to ſporte, is reckened mery and ciuill: He that paſſeth degree, is comp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a rayler, what maner of felowes are the Paraſites, and ſtage Players, and other light and fooliſh men. But he which altogether abhorreth Maygames
<pb facs="tcp:19634:77"/> is iudged beaſtly, and vplandiſhe. But wée muſt diligently take heede, leſſe through our bourdyng wee offende any man: that there be not immoderate co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceites, not filthy, not fooliſh. The work of Apothegmes collected of Eraſmus ſhall miniſter many mery toyes. And as concernyng that pleaſantneſſe of life whiche is remnant: who that ſhewes himſelf delectable in ſuche ſorte, as rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon requireth, he is called eaſie, gentell, courtiſe: and Facilitie is reckened Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diocritie. He whiche paſſeth the meane, if he be ledde with no occaſion, is to be compted ouer eaſie, and pliant: but if for his owne profit, he is to be eſteemed a flatterer. But he whiche altogether diſſenteth and departeth from meane and reaſon, and ſheweth himſelfe ſadde in all reſpects, he is to be thought teſtif, and churliſh, and worthie of al mennes hatred, with that vncourteiſe ſadneſſe, and rude grauitie, and vnthankefull to wiſe men. A certayne ſadde ſageneſſe in countenance ſéemeth to be ingraffed in certayne, what one is geuen to that Crito of Terence: which if it be natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall,
<pb facs="tcp:19634:78"/> ſurely it can neither be called pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly good, nor euill. It ſhalbe reckened good, if it agree to right reaſon. But there is a certaine ſecte of menne which cloke fooliſhneſſe in their face and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenaunce, and alſo in their ieſture, iet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and communication. Whoſe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectate grauity ratified by lewd cuſtom, is wonte to appeare very fooliſhe vnto witty men, and more rightlie informed vnto humanity. The laſt member of ſober moode doth teache that the paum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pering and apparelling of the carcaſe is to be moderated, and ſeemelineſſe to be kepte in it as in other matters, leſſe ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ouer curious care and riotte, or els carterlye and vnnaturall ſlouenry and vncleanlineſſe be reproued. For this vertue which conſiſteth of adourning a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable for the commodity of the body, &amp; neceſſity of nature is a meane betwixt ſuperfluity and filth. Let the apparell than be moderate, cleane, fit for the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy: and conueniente for vſe, not for foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhneſſe, and rediculous oſtentacion, what one the barbarous and outlandiſh is wont to be; let it be applied to the
<pb facs="tcp:19634:78"/> perſons accordyng to their dignitie and riches: and to kinde, to age, to place, to time, and to honeſt cuſtome. One be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eemeth noble and riche men, another the baſe and poore: one men, another women: one olde fathers, another the galant youthe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="chapter">
               <head>Of Intemperance and her two partes. Cap. xxxvij.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Ntemperancie, is a redineſſe conſeting to deſiers againſte reaſon: which Cice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro in his fourth boke <hi>Tuſculanaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> queſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionum</hi> doth define, a ſwaruing from al vnderſtanding, and from righte reaſon, ſo bended from the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reſcript of reaſon, that by no meanes the appetites ſenſual neither can be ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led nor yet repreſſed. The parts of this vice are two. One which verily addic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth
<pb facs="tcp:19634:79"/> her ſelfe vnto pleaſures: the other which doth nothing at all. Throughe her men do ruſh hedlong after the vſage of beaſts into al delices, the Empire of Reaſon throwen away. Through this, by the rudeneſſe of minde ſome (as it were with a certaine abaſhmente) are made dull vnto all paſtaunces, and alſo do reiect and contempne honeſt and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary delighte without occaſion. But theſe I iudge a man may ſéeke, and find a fewe, which through a certayne Bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſhneſſe would ſo abhorre all paſtime, wherewith Nature is cheefely delited, that they may be intreated with no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectation. The better ſort by a greate deale are wont to go aſtray in the other parte, and to géeue to muche ſcope vnto pleaſure, which temperaunce doth bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del by the Squire of reaſon: who being collocated betweene thoſe two vices, dothe alwaies laye claime to that preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous &amp; peculier Mediocritie of Vertue.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="38" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:19634:79"/>
               <head>Of the coniunction of Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues amonge them ſelues, the difference and excellencie. Cap. xxxviij.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Ll Vertues, which nowe are abſolute, and brought vnto the perfection of reaſon, are ſo connected together amonge them ſelues with a certayne mutuall copula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as the members of our bodie: they do ſo agrée in amible concord as muſical Harmonie. This is that manifold or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Ringes, whiche Plato writeth to be drawen vnto of the Lodeſtone.</p>
               <p>For you ſhal not cal him perfectly and truly a prudent man, which ſame is not both iuſt, and valiaunt, and temperate: neither iuſt, who wanteth the reſt: nor valiaunte, nor Temperate, who is not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urniſhed with the felowſhip of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidue, although he be conuerſaunt more commonly in one Vertue, than in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. But the vnperfecte vertues are
<pb facs="tcp:19634:80"/> not ſo yoked together that they may make as it weare a conſente and agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Wee haue heard that Socrates was Temperate and Modeſt: yet that bourding whiche is ſayde to haue béene peculiar vnto him, when as he woulde reprehende the vnſkilfulneſſe of others ſo greedely, can not eſcape the checke of arrogancie. But truly that great pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cience and Temperaunce of Iob publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in holy Scriptures was moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fet of all others. But not ſo many ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples are alledged of this abſolute Vertue: yet many maye be diſcloſed of the vnperfect. Som vertues excell o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in excellencie and operation: as Prudencie whoſe Harboroughe is pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in the minde, and is occupied in the out findinge of trouthe, ſhe is preferred before Temperaunce whiche modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth delices, and appoynteth a meane vnto all thinges, vnto whom a place is aſſigned in the deſiringe facultye of the ſoule. Iuſtice paſſeth Fortitude becauſe ſhe preſerueth the equality of humayne ſociety, and hath no certaine habitation, but is indifferently ſpred abrode vnto
<pb facs="tcp:19634:80"/> all partes of the Soule: this ought to be buſied in deſpiſing of perils, and oughte to bee ſituated in the Vertue of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grie Soule: what ſoeuer verily be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect vnto theſe cheefe Vertues, as they are lower in order, ſo be they in ſtateli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, by reaſon that ſome of them are vnder others: neither forthwith ſhould bee referred vnto the greateſte good, whiche thoſe principall Fountaynes do nexte conſider, but euery one to their proper beginninges, and ſhoulde haue regard of vs rather then of felicity: ſith not they of their owne power, but by thoſe foure Capitalles may be ſtraight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnto God him ſelfe, who is the end of all good thinges. To this wiſhed marke, and eternal felicitie we attaine, by the operation of Vertue verily (as in the beginning it is expreſſed) yet the which God him ſelfe may make proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous vnto vs, through his Clemencie: to whom be due all praiſe, honoure and glory for euer and euer. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notice">
            <pb facs="tcp:19634:81"/>
            <p>This booke tranſlated by Iohn Charlton, late fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low of Exetre Colledge, in Oxford, &amp; now Schole maister of Wyrkſop, in the countie of Notting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham.</p>
            <q>Mors vltima Linea rerum.</q>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:19634:81"/>
            <head>The Table.</head>
            <list>
               <item>OF the ende and partes of Morall Science. Cap. i.</item>
               <item>Of the end of man, and the Soueraigne good. Cap. ii.</item>
               <item>Of Affections. Cap. iii</item>
               <item>Of Loue. Cap. iiii.</item>
               <item>Of deſire and hope. Cap. v.</item>
               <item>Of Gladneſſe. Cap. vi,</item>
               <item>Of hatred and anger and like affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, Cap. vii.</item>
               <item>Of Sadneſſe. Cap. viii.</item>
               <item>Of Feare. Cap. ix.</item>
               <item>Of Boldneſſe. Cap. x.</item>
               <item>Of Vertue and her diuiſion and Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall. Cap. xi</item>
               <item>Of Prudencie Cap. xii.</item>
               <item>Of Domeſticall gouernaunce. Cap. xiii,</item>
               <item>Of Politike gouernaunce Cap. xiiii.</item>
               <item>O Vices contrary to vviſdom Cap xv.</item>
               <item>Of Iuſtice Cap xvi.</item>
               <item>Of the partes of Iuſtice Cap xvii.</item>
               <item>Of the ſix partes of Iuſtice conſtituted
<pb facs="tcp:19634:82"/> of Cicero, and theyr Vices, and of ſome other vvhich be vvelnie of the ſame nature cap, xviii</item>
               <item>Of Godlineſſe cap. xix.</item>
               <item>Of Reuerence, Cap. xx</item>
               <item>Of Trouth, cap. xxi</item>
               <item>Of Reuengement, Cap. xxii</item>
               <item>Of Thanke, cap. xxiii</item>
               <item>Of compaſſion, Cap. xxiiii</item>
               <item>Of Liberality and vices contrary to this, Auarice and Prodigalitie, cap. xxv</item>
               <item>Of Magnificence Cap. xxvi</item>
               <item>Of Frendſhip cap. xxvii</item>
               <item>Of Iniuſtice Cap. xxviii</item>
               <item>Of Fortitude cap. xxix</item>
               <item>Of Confidence and Magnanimitie Cap. xxx</item>
               <item>Of pacience and perſeuerance, cap xxxi</item>
               <item>Of the Vices betvveene vvhiche Forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude is placed cap. xxxii</item>
               <item>Of Temperaunce cap. xxxiii</item>
               <item>Of Continence and abſtinence cap. xxxiiii</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:19634:82"/>
               <item>Of Clemencie. Cap. xxxv</item>
               <item>Of Modeſtie Cap. xxxvi</item>
               <item>Of Intemperaunce and her tvvo partes, cap. xxxvii</item>
               <item>Of the coniunction of Vertues amonge <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hem ſelues the difference and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>encie. Cap. xxxviii</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>printer's device of William Howe (McKerrow 142)</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>¶ Theſe are to be ſolde, at the Southweſt doore of Poules Churche.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:19634:83"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:19634:83"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:19634:84"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:19634:84"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:19634:85"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:19634:85"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:19634:86"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:19634:86"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:19634:87"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:19634:87"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:19634:88"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:19634:88"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:19634:89"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:19634:89"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:19634:90"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:19634:90"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:19634:91"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:19634:91"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:19634:92"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:19634:92"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:19634:93"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:19634:93"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:19634:94"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:19634:94"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:19634:95"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:19634:95"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
